<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The araignement of Mr. Persecution: presented to the consideration of the House of Commons, and to all the common people of England wherein he is indicted, araigned, convicted, and condemned of enmity against God, and all goodnesse, of treasons, rebellion, bloodshed, &amp;c. and sent to the place of execution. In the prosecution whereof, the Jesuiticall designes, and secret encroachments of his defendants, Sir Symon Synod, and the John of all Sir Johns, Sir Jonh Presbiter, upon the liberty of the subject id detected, and laid open, / by yongue Martin Mar-Preist, son to old Martin the Metrapolitane. This is licensed, and printed according to holy order, but not entered into the Stationers monopole.</title>
            <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90227</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O620</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E276_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209849</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868703</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868703</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90227)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 46:E276[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The araignement of Mr. Persecution: presented to the consideration of the House of Commons, and to all the common people of England wherein he is indicted, araigned, convicted, and condemned of enmity against God, and all goodnesse, of treasons, rebellion, bloodshed, &amp;c. and sent to the place of execution. In the prosecution whereof, the Jesuiticall designes, and secret encroachments of his defendants, Sir Symon Synod, and the John of all Sir Johns, Sir Jonh Presbiter, upon the liberty of the subject id detected, and laid open, / by yongue Martin Mar-Preist, son to old Martin the Metrapolitane. This is licensed, and printed according to holy order, but not entered into the Stationers monopole.</title>
                  <author>Overton, Richard, fl. 1646.</author>
                  <author>Robinson, Henry, 1605?-1664?,</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 45 [i.e. 46], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Martin Claw Clergie [i.e. Richard Overton], printer to the reverend Assembly of Divines, and are to be sould at his shop in Toleration Street, at the signe of the Subjects Liberty, right opposite to Persecuting Court.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Europe [i.e. London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Martin Mar-Priest = Richard Overton.</note>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Henry Robinson.</note>
                  <note>The imprint is false; "published by Overton's own press" (Brailsford, H.N. "The levellers and the English revolution", p.54).</note>
                  <note>The first leaf contains an order to print.</note>
                  <note>Page numbers 30-46 misnumbered 29-45.</note>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Puritans --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="decree">
            <pb facs="tcp:121057:1"/>
            <head>Die Saturni, Apr. 6. 1645.</head>
            <p>It is <hi>Decreed,</hi> and <hi>Ordained</hi> by the reverend <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> now aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in <hi>holy Convocation,</hi> that Dr. <hi>Burgeſſe,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> doe returne thankes unto the worthy Authour of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> intituled, <hi>The Araigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Perſecution,</hi> for his pious endevoures, and vigilant care he hath taken therein, at the intreaty of this <hi>Synod:</hi> And it is further <hi>Ordained,</hi> that they doe deſire him to print and publiſh the ſaid Treatiſe forthwith, and that it be commended to the people, as a <hi>divine Hand-Maide</hi> to the right underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the <hi>Directory:</hi> And it is yet furcher Decreed and Ordained, that none ſhall preſume to print or reprint the ſaid Treatiſe, but whome he ſhall authorize under his own hand writing till this moſt <hi>Holy Synod</hi> ſhall take furuther Order.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <head>Scribes.</head>
                     <item>Henry Roborough,</item>
                     <item>Adoniran Byfeild,</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoynt my Cozen MARTIN CLAW-CLERGIE <hi>Printer</hi> to the <hi>reverend Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> and none elſe, to <hi>Print this Treatiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yongue MARTIN MAR-PREIST,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Araignement OF Mr. PERSECUTION: Preſented to the CONSIDERATION OF THE HOUSE OF COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and to all the COMMON PEOPLE of <hi>England WHEREIN HE IS INDICTED, ARAIGNED, CONVICTED, AND CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned</hi> of <hi>emnity againſt God, and all Goodneſſe, of Treaſons, Rebellion, Bloodſhed, &amp;c.</hi> and ſent to the place of <hi>Execution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the proſecution whereof, the</hi> Jeſuiticall Deſignes, <hi>and</hi> ſecret Encroachments <hi>of his D<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendants, Sir SYMON SYNOD, and the JOHN of all Sir JOHNS, Sir JONH PRESBITER, upon the Liberty of the Subject is detected, and laid open,</hi> By Yongue MARTIN MAR-PREIST, Son to old MARTIN the Metrapolitane.</p>
            <p>This is Licenced, and printed according to Holy Order, but not Entered into the Stationers Monopole.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Anglia MARTINIS diſce ſavere tuis.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>EUROPE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed by <hi>MARTIN CLAW CLERGIE,</hi> Printer to the <hi>Reverend Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> and are to be ſould at his Shop in <hi>Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Street,</hi> at the <hi>Signe</hi> of the <hi>Subjects Liberty,</hi> right oppoſite to <hi>Perſecuting Court.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121057:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121057:2"/>
            <head>TO THE REVEREND LEARNED THE PROLO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutor, Aſſoſſors, the Commiſſioners of the Church of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the reſt of the venerable Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, now ſitting in holy Convocation at <hi>Weſtminſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sirs,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>According to my duty at your</hi> divine entreaty, <hi>I have reduced thoſe</hi> pious inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons <hi>received from you, into ſuch a</hi> pleaſing forme, <hi>as I hope, ſhall not only</hi> affect, <hi>but abundantly</hi> edefie <hi>the people of this</hi> Kingdome <hi>under your</hi> holy Jurisdiction; <hi>for conſidering your</hi> ſpirituall care <hi>over them, and how your time hath been taken up wholy in the procurement of that</hi> ſacred Ordinance for Tythes, <hi>wiſely thought on before the</hi> Directory, <hi>for</hi> he is an Infidell and denyeth the faith, that doth not provide for his family: <hi>your late</hi> humble Advice <hi>digeſted into ſeverall</hi> Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: <hi>your ſore travill and paine you have daly ever ſince your</hi> holy Convocation <hi>undergon, to</hi> bring to birth <hi>his</hi> Holyneſſe, <hi>Sir</hi> JOHN PRESBYTER; <hi>and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your toyleſome endeavours for the Henone of your</hi> holy cloth, <hi>I have therefore more willingly become your</hi> Joyrnoman <hi>to eaſe</hi> your Burthen <hi>in this</hi> your toyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome time of Deformation; <hi>and having thus prepar'd my</hi> endeavoures, <hi>fit for the</hi> puolike vew, <hi>I am emboldned to</hi> Dedicate <hi>them unto</hi> your divine protection, <hi>not doubting of the</hi> ſacred impoſition of your hands upon them, <hi>to ſanctifie them unto the people, as,</hi> truly Presbyterean, <hi>that comeing</hi> forth <hi>with</hi> your Claſſicall Authority, <hi>they may obtaine a</hi> reverent eſtimation <hi>with them. And ſeeing I have made ſuch a happy</hi> beginning, <hi>I doubt not of an</hi> anſwerable encouragement <hi>from you to</hi> proceed <hi>as I have begun, but a ſmall matter will pleaſe</hi> MARTIN, <hi>if you</hi> ſanctifie <hi>him with the</hi> Benediciae <hi>of a</hi> Cornelian Benefice <hi>of 400. l. per annum, to</hi> knocke downe <hi>the</hi> Anabaptſts, Browniſts, <hi>&amp;c. with your thumping, bumping,</hi> Presbyterean, Claſſicall CLUB, <hi>that ſhall ſuffice</hi> pro tempore, <hi>and withall to gratifie him with the De me of</hi> Pauls <hi>Houſe that's but a ſmall matter, it will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his</hi> worſhip <hi>very well for the preſent, and afterwards you may doe, as it ſhall ſeem beſt to your divine wiſedomes aeeording to his beſt deſervings therein; he is a ſingular man in ſuch a buſines, and wants nothing but</hi> preforment; <hi>you doe not thinke, neither doth it enter into your hearts, how</hi> reverend Yongue MARTIN <hi>can</hi> thunder-thump <hi>the</hi> Pulpit, <hi>O, he can</hi> ſtaer <hi>moſt devnitly, raile and bawle moſt fervently, ſtorme moſt tempeſtiouſly even till be</hi> foame at mouth <hi>moſt preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; Oh how be can ſpetter't out! O theſe cauſed</hi> Anabapriſts, <hi>theſe wicked</hi> Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, <hi>theſe Hecetickes, theſe Sciſmatickes, theſe Sectaries; O</hi> MARTIN <hi>hath it at his fingers end, ha's an</hi> Vniverſity man, <hi>skild in the</hi> Tongues and Sciences, and can ſophiſtioue any Text, O he is excellent at falſe Gloſſes, and Schola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke Interpretations, he can wreſt the Scriptures moſt nearly, tell the people
<pb facs="tcp:121057:3"/>
it is thus and thus in the Originall, an excellent man to make a Presbyter! <hi>and O</hi> Bretheren, <hi>if</hi> MARTIN <hi>thus delude the people &amp; thraſh thoſe Hereticks in hope ſure</hi> MARTIN <hi>ſhall be partaker of his hope, you will not</hi> muzle the oxe that trendeth out your corne; <hi>no,</hi> MARTIN <hi>hath better eſteeme of the</hi> Aſſembly, <hi>he doth not once ſuppoſe, that like</hi> Bell's <hi>Aſſembly of Prieſts they'l devoure all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and leave nothing for</hi> MARTIN, <hi>but it is no matter,</hi> MARTIN <hi>will be content with hard meats rather then deſert the ſervice of ſuch on holy, ſuch a reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Aſſembly, ſuch a</hi> Quagmire <hi>of</hi> croaking skip-jacke Presbyters, <hi>ſuch is his zeale and pious affection to the Cauſe, he is reſolved to worke with his awne hands, rather then be troubleſome: Thus committing his endeavoures to your</hi> learned Conſultations, pious Debates, <hi>and</hi> ſacred Concluſions <hi>he reſts in expectation of his Reward,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours humbly devoated in all Synoddicall, Claſſicall, Conſiſtoreall, or Predicatory Function, till death us depars,
Yongue MARTIN MAR-PREIST, Son to old MARTIN the Metrapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litane.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To his Freind the Authour upon his Booke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>'Twas boldly ventured to ſet upon</l>
               <l>This foule blacke Feind, mad <hi>PERSECUTION,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pluto's</hi> Grand Agent, whom the world beſide,</l>
               <l>Durſt not but fawne upon, thou'ſt tane, and try'd:</l>
               <l>Thy paines ſure have been great, to ſeeke him out,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt encompaſt <hi>Europe</hi> all about,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sottiſh, Engliſh, Iriſh</hi> Climates too,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt trac'd'ore, to ſee what things they doe:</l>
               <l>What was the cauſe that ſo much blood was ſhed</l>
               <l>In all thoſe places? Why rents and ſad diviſions</l>
               <l>In Kingdomes once made happy? now the viſions</l>
               <l>Of woefull ruine; Spectacles for time,</l>
               <l>To write deſtructions everlaſting line.</l>
               <l>Thanke then Yongue <hi>MARTIN</hi> for his love and care,</l>
               <l>T'impart to theo, who theſe proud actours are,</l>
               <l>And let him have thy prayers, ſo thou ſhalt be,</l>
               <l>As much belov'd of virteous men as he.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121057:3"/>
            <head>THF ARAIGNEMENT OF PERSECUTION.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Certaine dreadfull, and ſevere Gentleman by name, <hi>Gods-ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance,</hi> of the Towne of <hi>Impartiallity,</hi> in the County of <hi>Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judgment,</hi> having a long time through the daily perſwations of his Kinſman, Mr. <hi>Long-ſufferance</hi> (an honeſt peaceable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, unwilling his enemie ſhould periſh) forborne to proceed againſt the great Enemie and Incendiary of mankind, Mr. <hi>Perſecution,</hi> according to his inquity, at length taking occaſion at his Kinſmans abuſed patience, forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with procurss a warrant from the Lord Cheife Juſtice, <hi>Peace-with-all-men,</hi> for the Conſtable, Mr. <hi>Reward-of-tyranny,</hi> to attach him; who takes with him two approved men of the Pariſh, old Mr. <hi>Woefull-experience,</hi> and honeſt Mr. <hi>Sound-judgment;</hi> and making ſtrict ſearch and inquiry after him front Religion to Religion, found him at length amongſt the Papiſts, under the name of Mr. <hi>Spaniſh-Inquiſition;</hi> but the ſuitable. Fox no ſooner perceived their <hi>Authority,</hi> but ſhrunke out of his Roman Papall Robe, and preſently turned <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> clad with an Engliſh Epiſcopall habit, under the name of Mr. <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> but Conſtable <hi>Reward-of-Tyranny,</hi> with old <hi>Woefull-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> and honeſt <hi>Sound-Judgment</hi> being acquainted with his trikes, made after him, whereat he caſt of his <hi>Lawne ſleeves, Hoode, Typpit,</hi> &amp;c and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, leaſt all Trades ſhould faile, became a zealous <hi>Covenanter,</hi> in the godly ſhape of a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> changing his name into <hi>Claſſicall Presbytrie</hi> (a new cheat to coſen the world), and then Scholer like, as if it had been for a goodly fat Benefice, in the twinkling of an eye jumpt out of <hi>Scotland</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> and turn'd a reverend <hi>Synodian,</hi> diſguiſ'd with a Sylogiſticall pair of Britches (ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving your preſence) in <hi>Bocardo,</hi> and ſnatching a Rhetoricall Caſſok he girt up his loynes with a Sophiſticall Girdle, and ran into the wilderneſſe of <hi>Tropes,</hi> and <hi>Figures,</hi> and there they had loſt him, had it not been for the <hi>Spirits Teaching,</hi> by whoſe direction they trac'd him through the various winding; ſubtile by-Pathes, ſecret tracts, and cunning Meanders the evening wolves,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121057:4"/>
wild Boares and Beaſts of the Forreſt in the briery thickets of Rhetoricall Gloſſes, Sophiſtications, and ſcholaſtick Interpretations had made, but being ſit to lay hands on him, the cunning: <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> vaniſh'd out of their ſight, and preſently <hi>takes Sanctuary,</hi> for lookeing about for him, Behold, he was <hi>doing his buſines</hi> (Sr. <hi>Beverence)</hi> in the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> thumping it devoutly, and moſt furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly like the <hi>Son of Thunder</hi> he <hi>ratl'd</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, &amp;c.</hi> letting his <hi>bolts</hi> (which according to the <hi>Proverbe</hi> were <hi>ſoone ſhot)</hi> ſly at randome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: but thinking to apprehend him, he skipt from them, from <hi>Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit</hi> to <hi>Pulpit,</hi> from <hi>Vniverſity</hi> to <hi>Vniverſity,</hi> from <hi>Colledge</hi> to <hi>Colledge,</hi> even through all the <hi>Pulpits, Vniverſities,</hi> and <hi>Colledges</hi> in <hi>Chriſtendome,</hi> and then he hied him from <hi>Parſonage</hi> to <hi>Parſonage,</hi> where the <hi>Parſons Wifes</hi> had thought to have hid him amongſt the <hi>Heards</hi> of <hi>Tyth Pigges,</hi> flockes of chickings, geeſe &amp;c. but that failing, he ran as if he had been wild through the <hi>Gleabe Land,</hi> and skipt over into a <hi>Tyth Cocko,</hi> and thought all had been <hi>cocke ſure;</hi> but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving they eſpy'd him, up ſtarts the Fox, and preſently faſt by the <hi>Synod</hi> he caught hold on the <hi>Altar,</hi> but fearing leaſt he ſhould be made a burnt Offering he vaniſhed into 12. <hi>Articles,</hi> but that buſineſſe not thriving, the next ſight that was made of him, was in a petitionary garbe in the behalfe of the <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> Miniſtors: And a thouſand other trickes, that I cannot reckon, he had; but one above all the reſt I muſt not forget, which was the <hi>maſter peace</hi> of all the reſt; for to bloke up all paſſages; ſtop all mouthes, and fortifie himſelfe round, he turn'd <hi>reverend Imprimatur:</hi> and here tho <hi>purſuers</hi> were at a ſtand, for all was as faſt as the <hi>Divel</hi> and tho <hi>Presbyters</hi> could make it, they ſought to Authority to open the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> and ſtill the <hi>Preſ-byters</hi> (as their cuſtome is) were in the way, that nothing could be done: Well, no good was to be done in publike, they then goe to it privatoly, and to worke a deliverance, fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to dangrous labour, and at length brought forth the villaine into publike vew, and notwithſtanding all his trickos detected, apprehended, and caried him to Juſtice <hi>Reaſon,</hi> who hauing examined the Malefactour, ſets downe his <hi>Examination,</hi> and binds over <hi>Gods-Vengance</hi> to proſecute the <hi>Malefactour</hi> at the next <hi>Aſſizes,</hi> and finding him not baylable, makes his <hi>Mittimus</hi> for the Cohſtable to commit him to the Goale, there to be kept in ſafe cuſtody with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Manupriſe</hi> till the, next <hi>Goale delivery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for the better underſtanding of this <hi>Araignment</hi> this enſuing Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue of the names of the ſeverall Officers of the Court is here annexed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Aſſizes</hi> held at the <hi>Araignment</hi> of <hi>Perſecution.</hi> 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Lord <hi>Parliament</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell role="label">The Judge</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <label>Juſtice</label>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Reaſon</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Humanity</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Conformity</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Juſtices the Peace.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:121057:4"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sir Charles-Royall-Prerogative.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The Kings <hi>Sergeant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sir Peter-proteſtant.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>The Kings Arturney.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir <hi>John-Equity</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>High-Sherriffe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Mr. <hi>Obedience</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Under Sherriffe.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Clarke. Cryer.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Mr.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Soveraignty-of-Chriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Power-of-Parliamentes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vnity-of-Kingdomes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nationall-Strength.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Setled-Peace.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Humaine-Society</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>Grand Jnqueſt.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vnited-Provinces.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Deſolate-Germany.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Blood-of-Primes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Publike-Good.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nationall-Wealth.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Civill-Government.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Domeſtick-Miſeries</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Mr.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Creation.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Goſpell.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Politique-power</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>State-policy.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Innocent-blood.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Good-ſamaritane.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Trueth-and-peace.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Orphan.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Jury of life and death.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Light-of-nature.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Day-of-judgement.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>National-loyalty.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Liberty-of-Subject</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> PER SECUTION.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Priſoner.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Mr. Gods-Vengence.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Proſecutour.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <label>Caffar</label>
                              <list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Chriſtian</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Martyrs</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Liberty-of Conſcience.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Evidences.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Sir <hi>Symon Synod</hi> and <hi>Sir John Presbyter.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Defendants.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>A new Jury for Life and Death endeavoured by Sir <hi>Symon Synod.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Mr.</label>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Satan</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Spaniſh-inquiſition.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Counſell-of-Trent.</hi>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Rude-multitude.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Sr. John Presbiter.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Scotch-government.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Falſe-prophets.</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>Sir <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Jury men.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Eccleſ.-Supremacy.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Pontificall-Revenue.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>High-commiſſion.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aſſembly-of-Divines.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:121057:5"/>
THus (Reader) the Court being compleat, for thy more ſpeedy progreſſion through the matter intended, ſuppoſe the tranſaction of many paſſages in theſe <hi>Aſſizes</hi> here in this <hi>Relation</hi> omitted, as needleſſe the repetion; the <hi>Eſſentialls</hi> thereof being ſo tedious (to the impatient Reader, yet not unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſeleſſe (I hope) to the diligent peruſer) for wherein without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to our preſent matter, an omiſſion may be, my ſilence for formality ſake gives place to a ſuppoſition thereof, otherwiſe I ſhall tranſgreſſe upon the Readers Patience. Thus then the <hi>Grand Inqueſt</hi> (the matter being thus far brought) fall into debate.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. Mr. <hi>Soveraignenity of Chriſt.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, our Lord of Lords, and King of Kings, whoſe Image and expreſſe prerogative I am, hath by the price of his blood, conſtituted himſelfe ſole <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>King</hi> ſo everover the <hi>Conſciences</hi> of men and therefore he chargeth his Houſholders, the <hi>Kings</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> to let the <hi>Tares</hi> and the <hi>Wheat</hi> grow together in the <hi>Field</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> untill the <hi>Harveſt</hi> the <hi>Day of Judgement,</hi> therefore this Malefactour <hi>Perſecution,</hi> in my Judgement, being in his <hi>Inclinations</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> altogether averſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, is an <hi>Arch-traitour</hi> to the <hi>Preagative Royall</hi> of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> over the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences of men, and therefore Lawfully and Juſtly charged with this <hi>Bill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. Mr. <hi>Power of Parliaments.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Verdict (Mr. <hi>Foreman)</hi> is, that <hi>Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> for Conſcience is Inconſiſtant with the <hi>Soveraignty</hi> of <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> for it divideth their <hi>Powers</hi> one againſt another, and in themſelves occaſioneth murmurings, grutchings, and repinings, which in in time breake forth into Conſpiracies, Rebellions, Inſurrections, &amp;c. as well to the prejudice of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignity, as to the ruine of the Subject; and which is more, the tendency, operation, and end of Perſecution, is to reduce the Power of Kingdomes and Parliaments from themſelves into the hands and diſpoſall of the Pontificall Clergie, according to the diveliſh Decree of Pope <hi>Paul 4. con. Trent lib. 5. p.</hi> 409. So that there can be no ſecurity for the Power of Majeſtracy, where Eccleſiaſticke vſurpation is predominant; for the greater their Power is, the the leſſe powerfull is Majeſtracy: wherefore I muſt needs conſent to the equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this <hi>Byll.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>3. <hi>Mr. Vnity-of-Kingdomes.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> ſhould I relate how through the diviliſh polecy and cruelty of this <hi>Perſecution for conſcience</hi> I have been ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed from betwixt Kingdomes, States, and Provinces to their utter deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in one an others ruine, I ſhould be unhappily too trobleſome: wherefore in ſhort, my <hi>verdict</hi> is concurrant with yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>4. Mr. <hi>Nationall-Strength.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> I conceive that you cannot be unſenſible that the Nationall ſtrength of Kingdomes and People conſiſts in the generall peace, as ſeverall members wiſely compacted in the naturall skin of one politike body: wherefore, to foſter this <hi>Malefactor</hi> amongſt a people, is to vender the ſtrength of a Kingdome to ruine, for he is a conſtant ſower of divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121057:5"/>
emulation, hatred, &amp;c. amongſt them: So that my <hi>verdict</hi> is not any wayes diſſenting from your judgment.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mr. <hi>Setled-Peace.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> By reaſon of <hi>Perſecution for conſcience,</hi> I can find no abſolute acceptance in any Kingdome or Nation throughout, Chriſtendome For he ſo poyſoneth all Nationall Pacifications, Leagues and Covenants, that their peace changeth with their Reigion; ſo that their peace cannot be truly ſetled whererefore my <hi>verdici</hi> is concurrant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>6. Mr. <hi>Humaine-Society.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr <hi>Foreman,</hi> My <hi>verdict</hi> is, what by experience you have all found, that he hath not only ſet Kingdomes at variance, but even ſat bee againſt ſon, and ſon againſt father, one friend againſt an other, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes them in one an others blood, to the deſtruction of all humaine ſociety: wherefore, I conceive this Charge againſt him is according to equiry.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>7. Mr. <hi>Blood-of-Princes.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> The blood of Kings, Rulers, and Governours; the Treaſons, Deſignes, and Conſpiracies againſt their perſons, whereof Hiſtory is full, and whereto our Age is not wanting, occaſioned by <hi>Perſecution,</hi> enforces my <hi>verdict</hi> in approbation of the <hi>Byll</hi> againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>7. Mr. <hi>Vnited-Provinces.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> Whoſoever readeth the Hiſtory of the <hi>Vnnited Prvinces,</hi> and conſidereth their wonderfull preſervation, flouriſhing ſtate and proſperity they enjoy, notwithſtanding their with waging of continuall warre with a forraigne Enemie, may clearly perceive, the great mercy of God vpon a Nation and People, that in tender to the conſciences one of an other, exclude, baniſh and extirpate <hi>Perſecution</hi> out of their Territories: wherofore I likewiſe conſent to the equity of the <hi>Byll</hi> given in againſt him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>8. Mr. <hi>Deſolate-Germany.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> Thoſe that doubt of the truth of this <hi>Byll,</hi> let them but looke upon the Germaine deſolations, depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations, warre, famine, and peſtilence occaſioned through papall ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy over our conſciences, and he may receive full ſatisfaction of the equity of this <hi>Byll.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>9. Mr. <hi>Publique-good.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> that which is deſtructive to the publique good is <hi>Treaſonable,</hi> and not to be ſuffered in a <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſtriketh at the <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> whoſe proper end is, that all may lead a <hi>Quiet</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> life under the publique <hi>Protection.</hi> But this Fellow, <hi>Perſecution,</hi> diverteth the publique good from the <hi>Generality</hi> to this or that <hi>Sort,</hi> to this or that <hi>prevailing Faction:</hi> ſo that where, or in what <hi>State</hi> ſoever he is <hi>Predominate,</hi> there is an impoſſibility of an equall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of the publique good, but even the better ſort, ſuch as ſtand for the good of others as well as their owne, and have hazarded their lives for the publique good againſt the common <hi>Enemy,</hi> as <hi>Anabaptiſts, Browniſts &amp;c.</hi> are by him deprived of the publique <hi>Liberty</hi> and <hi>Freedome</hi> of the <hi>Subject,</hi> for which they have engaged <hi>Eſtate</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> Therefore Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> my <hi>Verdect</hi> upon the <hi>Bill</hi> is <hi>BILLA VERA.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>0. <hi>Nationall-wealth.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> that which is the Ruine of Nationall
<pb facs="tcp:121057:6"/>
Wealth is deſtructive to the very <hi>Being</hi> and continuance of <hi>Nations, King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,</hi> and <hi>States:</hi> for it bringeth <hi>Devaſtation</hi> and <hi>Depopulation</hi> thereof, and ſo not to be ſuffered. But this <hi>Perſecution</hi> for Conſcience ſtirreth up <hi>Warres</hi> and <hi>Bloodſhed,</hi> in <hi>Nations, Kingdomes,</hi> and <hi>States,</hi> which conſumeth their <hi>Wealth,</hi> devoureth their <hi>Fruit,</hi> burneth and deſtroyeth their <hi>Cities, Townes,</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> and throweth all into a <hi>Wilderneſſe.</hi> Therefore Mr. <hi>Foreman</hi> you have my conſent to the verity of this <hi>Byll.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Foreman.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, we have ſpent much time, and our <hi>verdict</hi> is expected, if you (12.) Mr. <hi>Civill-Government.</hi> and Mr. (13.) <hi>Domesticke-Miſeries,</hi> be agreed with us in your <hi>verdict,</hi> there remaineth nothing, but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorſment hereof with <hi>Billa-Vera.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
               <p>Wee are agreed with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>This paſt, the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> give in their verdict or <hi>Inditement</hi> endorſed with <hi>Billa vera,</hi> whereby the Malefactor Perſecution is made a lawfull priſoner, to be brought forth to the Barre, and to be put upon the Jury of life and death.</p>
            <p>Whereupon the <hi>Clarke</hi> (the month of the Court) commands the Goaler to ſet forth <hi>Perſecution</hi> to the <hi>Barre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Goaler ſets forth</hi> Perſecution <hi>to the Barre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Indictment.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
               <p>Perſecution, <hi>Hold up thy Hand, and heare thy</hi> Indictment. Perſe-ſecution, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſtandeſt Indicted in this</hi> County <hi>of</hi> Juſt-Judgment <hi>by the name of</hi> Perſecution, <hi>late of the Towne of</hi> Tyranny, <hi>in the</hi> County <hi>of</hi> Martyrdome, <hi>by</hi> Gods-Vengance, <hi>of the Towne of</hi> Impartiallity, <hi>in the</hi> County <hi>of</hi> Juſt-Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>That thou art an enemy to God and all goodneſſe, a Traytor to Kings and Princes, their perſons, Crownes and Dignities divider of them one againſt an other, and of Kingomes and people in themſelves, and that thou art guilty of the warre and bloodſhed at preſent in this Land, yea almoſt of all the blood of the whole earth from the blood of righteous</hi> Abell <hi>unto the blood of theſe preſent times, contrary to the peace of our Soveraigne Lord the King, his crowne and dignity: How <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou</hi> Perſecution, <hi>art thou guilty of this Treaſon, Rebellion and bloodſhed in manner and forme as thou ſtandeſt Indicted, or not guilty?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
               <p>Not guilty.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
               <p>By whom wilſt thou be tryed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
               <p>By God and my Countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>Then an <hi>Impannell</hi> being returned, the Clarke ſaith,</p>
            <sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>You good men that are</hi> Impanneled <hi>between our Soveraigne Lord the King, and the priſoner at the</hi> Barre, <hi>anſwer to your names at the firſt call upon paine and perill that may fall thereon.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>They all anſwer to their names.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
               <p>Cryer, make Proclamation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cryer</speaker>
               <p>o—yes—If any man can informe my Lord the Kings Juſtices, the Kings Sergeant, or the Kings
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121057:6"/>
Atturney before this Inqueſt be taken, between our Soveraigne Lord the King, and the priſoner at the Barre, let them come forth and they ſhalbe heard; for the priſoner ſtands at the Barreupon his deliverance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
               <p>You the priſoner that is called to the Bar, theſe men which you have heard called, and perſonally appeare, ſhall paſſe between our Soveraigne Lord the King and you, upon tryall of your life and death, if you will <hi>challenge</hi> them, or any of them, you muſt ſpeake unto them or any of them as they come to the Booke to be ſworne, before they be ſworne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Priſoner.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, let me humbly crave liberty to <hi>Challenge</hi> this Jury, who though my Lord in all probability they be honeſt Gentlemen, yet my bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, education, nature and courſe of life is not ſo well known unto them, as unto divers other Geentlemen (of worth and quality) here preſent, indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent men, of far more eſteem in the world, more able to diſcerne my cauſe, &amp; the evidence mine accuſars ſhall bring: Beſides my Lord, theſe men of the <hi>Jury</hi> are men poſſeſt with an inveterate hatred and malice againſt me, and are parties in my <hi>Indictment;</hi> for together with the Grand Inqueſt they conſpired toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt me, and provoaked <hi>Gods-Vengance</hi> to proſecute againſt me: now for me to be tryed by mine accuſars and mortall enemies I hope your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip cannot conceive it equall or legall: wherefore my Lord, I beſeech you have mercy upon me, conſider the blood of the innocent, leaſt it be a prey to the malice of envy, and let more indifferent men be choſen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judge</speaker>
               <p>Perſecution, I much wonder at thy impudence in excepting againſt ſuch a <hi>Jury,</hi> yet ſo far as in equity I may I am willing for juſtice ſake, to grant the utmoſt the Law affords.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Priſoner.</speaker>
               <p>I humbly thanke your Lordſhip, the Lord bleſſe your Honour, and I beſeech your Honour for the aſſiſtance of Sir <hi>Symon Synod.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judg</speaker>
               <p>Well then let Sir <hi>Symon</hi> be cal'd into the Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clarke</speaker>
               <p>Call Sir <hi>Symon Synod.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crier</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sir Symon Synod,</hi> come into the Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judge</speaker>
               <p>Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> if you can further his Majeſties ſervice, in the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of others in the roome of thoſe Perſecution doth except againſt to Mr. Sherriffe to be impanneled, you are commauded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir <hi>Symon Synod</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My Lord, ſince it is your Lordſhids pleaſure with the conſent of this Honourable Bench, that I ſhall be ſerviceable to him
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121057:7"/>
I ſhall moſt willingly propoſe to his conſideracion perſons of ſufficient worth and eſtimation in the World, that are not prejudiciall to the Perſon of the Priſoner, neither are parties in his accuſation, indiſſerent men, acquainted with his life and converſation, able to diſcerne the evidence, that ſhall be brought in again <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, men whom I ſhall commend unto your Lordſhips acceptance for ſoundneſſe of judgment, and ſingular Piety in the cauſe of the Cle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, this being a matter which concernes them in an high nature: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by your Lordſhips favour I ſhall propoſe thoſe if (if no better can be procured) to wit, Mr. <hi>Satan,</hi> Mr, <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> Mr. <hi>Councell-of-Trent,</hi> Mr. <hi>High-Commiſſion,</hi> Mr. <hi>Aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbly-of-Divines,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rude-Multitude,</hi> Sr. <hi>John Presbyter,</hi> mine only ſon, Mr. <hi>Scotch Government,</hi> Mr. <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>-Prophets,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eccleſiaſticall-Supremacy,</hi> Mr. <hi>Pontificall-Revenue:</hi> Theſe never ſailed the deſignes of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> who in all Ages have <hi>endevoured</hi> the Advancement of the Church of God, the <hi>Tribe</hi> of <hi>Levi:</hi> wherefore this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Caſe that concernes their Advancement, which above all things in the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld is to be endevoured, I am emboldned to propound them unto Mr. <hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe,</hi> for the <hi>Tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll</hi> of this <hi>Priſoner.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Simm,</hi> this is a ſtrange <hi>Jury</hi> you propoſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juſtice <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My <hi>Lord;</hi> it is according to the nature of the <hi>Clergy, can you expect</hi> Grapes <hi>of</hi> Thornes, <hi>or</hi> Figges <hi>of</hi> Thiſtles? if you ſhall but according to Reaſon conſider of their <hi>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es</hi> and <hi>Pretences,</hi> which indeed beare a ſpecious ſhew, you ſhall find them no better then ravening <hi>Woolves</hi> in <hi>Sheepes</hi> Cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juſtice <hi>Humanity.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> it cannot ſtand with Humanity, much leſſe wich <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Equity,</hi> that a Caſe which concernes the generall good of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind ſhould be refer'd to the <hi>Verdict</hi> of ſuch anhumane <hi>Jury.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kings <hi>Ser.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My <hi>Lord</hi> there be divers of them whom <hi>Royall Prerogative</hi> hath called in to his Aſſiſtance, and at this day I conceive maketh uſe of them for the Eſtabliſhing the Liberty of the Subject and the <hi>Proteſtant Religi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> on,</hi> ſo that for my part I cannot ſee how all of them can be condemned.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kings <hi>Attorn.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> a great part of them are Props to the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Juſtice <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>My <hi>Lord,</hi> what though <hi>Royall Prerogative</hi> and the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion</hi> ſhould be founded upon them? muſt they therfore be conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Anthentick? <hi>non ſequitur:</hi> and for the Liberty of the Subject, though they may be uſed as a Gloſſe; yet Reaſon will tell you, that they are as direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppoſite to it, as the <hi>Zenith</hi> is to the <hi>Antipodes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sr. Simon,</hi> I cannot in Equity permit ſuch unworthy Perſons to be on the <hi>Jury,</hi> only Mr. <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines,</hi> Sr. <hi>John Presbiter</hi> and Mr. <hi>Scotch-governement</hi> are commanded to attend the <hi>Court,</hi> for the ſervice of the <hi>King,</hi> if occaſion be.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121057:7"/>
                  <hi>Then the former Jury being ſworne, &amp;c. the Goaler is co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>anded to ſet fortb</hi> PERSECUTION <hi>to the Barre</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Clar.</hi> PERSECUTION, hold up thy hand: Looke upon him Maſters of the Jury, hearken to his cauſe, You ſhall underſtand, that he ſtands indicted in this County of <hi>Juſt-judgment,</hi> by the name of PERSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUTION, &amp;c. Upon this Indictment he hath beene Arraigned, and thereto hath pleaded <hi>not guilty,</hi> and for his tryall hath put himſelfe upon God and the Countrey, which Countrey are you: your <hi>Charge</hi> is to enquire whether he be guilty of this Treaſon, murder, &amp;c. in manner and forme as he ſtands Indicted, or not guilty: And heare your Evidence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any man can give Evidence, or can ſay any thing againſt the Priſoner let him come forth, for the Priſoner ſtands upon his deliverance.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>Clar. call</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gods-Vengance.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Chriſtian.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Martyrs.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Lib. Conſ.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <label>Crier.</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Gods-Vengance.</hi> here.</item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Chriſtian.</hi> here.</item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Martyrs.</hi> here.</item>
                           <item>Gaffar <hi>Lib. Conſ come forth &amp; proſecute, or you forfeite your Recogniſance</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <item>I cannot get in my Lord Sir <hi>Symon</hi> keeps me out. O! murder, murther, my Lord.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
               <p>What is the matter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lib. Conſ.</speaker>
               <p>My Lord, Sir <hi>Symon Synod</hi> is like to pull out my throate with the revenous Clawes of an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Scotch-Government</hi> was fit to ſtab me with his <hi>Scotch dagger,</hi> and the <hi>John</hi> of all Sr. <hi>Johns,</hi> Sr. <hi>John Presbyter</hi> with his <hi>Claſſicall Club</hi> would beat out my braines: For my Lord, they are affraid I ſhould come into your Honours preſence, leaſt I ſhould find entertainment in this Kingdome, and ſo Mr. <hi>Pontificall-Revenue</hi> turne Seperate from the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peace there, every man keep ſilence upon paine of impriſonment: make way there for</hi> Liberty-of-Conſcience; Jemmy, <hi>put up thy dagger;</hi> Sir Symon <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oe paire your nalles;</hi> Sir John, <hi>away with your Club, that</hi> Liberty-of-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience <hi>may come into the</hi> Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <p>The Witneſſes being come in, they are ſworne every one according to their knowledge to give in a true Evidence for the King againſt the Priſoner at the Barre.</p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gods-Vengance, ſtand up, what can you ſay for the King againſt the Priſoner at the Bar?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>GODS-VENGANCE</head>
               <p>My Lord, I have from the beginning dilligently obſerved the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> and <hi>inclinations</hi> of this <hi>Priſoner,</hi> eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to have been ſo averſe to God and all goodneſſe, that his Actions in all <hi>Nations Kingdomes</hi> and <hi>St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121057:8"/>
amongſt <hi>Societyes</hi> and people, have been in direct Enmity to the end of Chriſts comming: for <hi>he came not to deſtroy mens Lives, but to ſave them Luk. 9. 56. Joh.</hi> 3. 17. But this fellow <hi>PERSECVTION,</hi> deſtroyeth both Life Temporall and Spirituall: he waſteth mens <hi>Eſtates,</hi> the more Godly and upright they are, the more <hi>cruell, raging</hi> and <hi>hatefull</hi> he is againſt them, he bringeth <hi>Miſery, Poverty</hi> and <hi>Beggery</hi> on their Wives and Children: yea my Lord, this <hi>Savage Blood-thirſty</hi> Wretch <hi>Hangeth, Burneth, Stoneth, Tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, Saweth a ſunder, Caſteth into the ſiery</hi> Fornace, <hi>into the Lions Denne, Teareth in peeces with</hi> Wild Horſes, <hi>Plucketh out the eyes, Roaſtet quicke, Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alive, Plucketh out the</hi> Tongues, <hi>Impriſoneth, Scourgeth, Revileth, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, yea, with</hi> Bell Booke <hi>and</hi> Candle, <hi>Belyeth, Cutteth the</hi> Eares, <hi>Slitteth the</hi> Noſe, <hi>Manacles the Hands, G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th the</hi> Mouthes, <hi>Whippeth Pil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oreth, Ban ſheth into remote Iſlands, makes them fly by wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> falls into</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts, <hi>Stigmatizeth ſome, and ſometimes maketh ſuch (ſo Stigmatized) when the wind turnes, to Stigmatize their freinds with</hi> Reproaches, Calumnies, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion <hi>of</hi> Conſcience <hi>&amp;c. Deprives</hi> them of the Communication of their Freinds, of all <hi>Releife,</hi> of <hi>Pen, Inke and Paper,</hi> Sep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Man and Wife, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives Parents of their Children and Children of their Parents, <hi>Impriſeneth</hi> men only <hi>for the diſcharge of a good Conſcience, Stoppeth Preſſes,</hi> whereby men cannot make their juſt defence, Suffers nothing to be <hi>Licenſed, Printed, Preached,</hi> or otherwiſe publiſhed, but what himſelfe alloweth, and having thus bound the hands and ſtopt the mouthes of all good men, then he comes forth in <hi>Print</hi> againſt them like an Armed man, and furiouſly aſſalts them, Exults and Exalts himſelfe over them, <hi>Feigneth</hi> Arguments for them and then like a Valiant Champion gives them a conquering Anſwere, and thus puts them to f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ight, and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſnes them with Revilings, Scanda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geries, and Opprob<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ions Nick-names, as <hi>Antinomians, Anabaptiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, Independants, Sciſmatiques, Heretiques &amp;c.</hi> Thus he dealeth with the Godly party: Yea, he forceth Millions to make <hi>Shipwracke of a good Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science,</hi> who for feare of ſuch inhumanity <hi>deny the Lord that bought them,</hi> to their finall condemnation. Oh! therefore (my Lord) if there be any Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells of Mercy, any tender Compaſſion in you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pitty the deſtitute, the Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, the tormted, who wander about in Sheepskinnes and in Goateskinnes in deſarts and in mountaines, in Dens and in Caves of the Earth, of whom the World is not worthy.</p>
               <p>Secondly, my Lord, he maketh a Nation guilty of all the righteous blood ſpilt upon the Earth; from the blood of <hi>Abel</hi> to the blood of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> and of all that are ſlayon upon the Earth; for it is all innocent blood that is ſhed in that caſe, purchaſed by the blood of Jeſus Chriſt, who <hi>came not to deſtroy, but to ſave mens lives;</hi> and therefore would have all taught in all Nations, that all might be perſwaded to the obedience of the truth, that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121057:8"/>
all might be ſaved: Therefore to kill the unbeleivor, as, <hi>Turke, Pagan, Jew, &amp;c.</hi> is to ſlay ſuch as <hi>Chriſt would have to live to repent,</hi> which muſt needs be <hi>Murder</hi> in the higheſt <hi>Nature: And curſed is he that ſhall ſtay an Innocent P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and all the people ſhall ſay</hi> Amen, <hi>Deut. 29. 25. The Land that ſheddeth In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Blood, Innocent blood ſhall be upon it. Deut.</hi> 19: 10: and <hi>Innocent Blood the</hi> Lord <hi>will not pardon. 2 King:</hi> 24. 4.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, my Lord, he occaſioneth Treaſons, Conſpicaſies, Reballions, Warres, Forreigne and Domeſticke, in all <hi>Nations</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> in the Earth, <hi>He</hi> divideth <hi>Prince</hi> againſt <hi>Prince,</hi> Kingdome againſt Kingdome, &amp; Kingdomes in themſelves, Breedeth and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>get<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth a Nationall hatred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and amongſt themſelves: he ſetteth Neighbour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Neighbour, Yea Father againſt Sonne and Sonne againſt Father, he breaketh the bonds of Peace and Freindſhip Nationall and Domeſticke, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>geth and Filleth the wholl Earth with blood and Violence: for what at this day is the Reaſon the Proteſtants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Blood of the Papiſts? but becauſe the Papiſts ſeeke theirs? they hate &amp; perſecute the Papiſts, becauſe the Papiſts hate and perſecute them: they would extirpate and roote out the Papiſts becauſe the Papiſts would doe the like to them. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, the Papiſts plot and conſpire againſt the Proteſtants, becauſe the Proteſtants will not ſuffer them to live amongſt them, but <hi>Baniſh, Impriſon, Hang, Draw, Quarter, and ſet up the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mbs of ſome of them</hi> (in open defiance to the God of heaven &amp; earth) <hi>upon the Gates of the City,</hi> who though unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily they be found <hi>Traitors</hi> to the <hi>Publique Pease and Politiqus Government,</hi> yet Nature might teach them to bury their Limbe, <hi>An Eye for an Eye, a Tooth for a Tooth, Blood for Blood,</hi> ſaith God: but now Blood cannot ſatisfie Inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane cruelty: If this be <hi>Canonicall,</hi> Let me have old <hi>Tobits Apochripha,</hi> who hazarded his life to bury the dead.</p>
               <p>Where two ſtand at Enmity, there muſt needs be Maſtery, or elſe no ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: When one knoweth tho other is his mortall Enemy, he will uſe all the Means, Strenght and Pollicy that he can to ſubdue him. This enrageth to all manner of Tyranny and bloodſhed, ſetteth one Kingdome againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, becauſe each knoweth and taketh each other for his deadly Enemy: Their faith being built upon this <hi>rotten &amp; devouring</hi> principle of <hi>forcing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences one of another.</hi> But if the Papiſt knew the Proteſtant, the Proteſtant the papiſt to love another: &amp; would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> moleſt or in the leaſt injure o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for their <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but live peaceably &amp; quietly one by another; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring one with another, and ſo of all Religions: What man would lift up his hand againſt his Neighbour? This could not but cond<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to a generall true ſetled Peace, to the wholl World. And in a ſhort time, the Enmity of Heart betweene the Papiſt &amp; Proteſtant &amp;c. would be quite worne ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Why ſhould we hate and deſtroy one another? are we no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> all the Creatures
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121057:9"/>
of one God? redeemed by one Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> this ſhould provoke us to Love and peace one towards another. If God have revealed more Light of the Goſpell to one then to another, ſhall the more knowing trample the ignorant under his feet? we ſhould carry our ſelves loving and meeke one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another, with <hi>Patience perſwading and exhorting the contrary minded proving if at any time God will turne their hearts,</hi> by this meanes the great <hi>Incendiary</hi> of the World, <hi>an inforced enraged Conſcience,</hi> would be at reſt. What is more neere and deere then our <hi>Conſciences?</hi> if that be enraged who can appeaſe it? if that be ſatisfied, what Content Joy or Peace like unto it? or what more mild, more Gentle or Loving? Therefore how tender ought we to be in Cafes of Conſcience? it is a <hi>Lion</hi> if enraged, a <hi>Lamb</hi> if appeaſed: it is all <hi>Honey</hi> or all <hi>Gall,</hi> enraged it is like the <hi>Wild Bore of</hi> the <hi>Forreſt,</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, it is like the <hi>Dove from the Arke:</hi> no greater Freind, no greater Foe.</p>
               <p>It is better therefore for Kingdomes to ſet the <hi>Conſcience</hi> free as in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Polonta, Tranſylvania &amp;c.</hi> and be at Peace in themſelves, then to bind and enforce it and be Rent in themſelves with <hi>Emulations, Heart-burnings, Conſpiracies, Rabellions &amp;c.</hi> If this <hi>Fiery Spirit</hi> were allaied, <hi>This ignorant Zeall of forcing all to beleive as we beleive, extinct: Nationall Feares, Jelouſies, and Hatred</hi> would ceaſe betwixt <hi>Nation and Nation, people and people:</hi> for as <hi>this violent Implacable Spirit</hi> ſuggeſteth <hi>Feares</hi> and <hi>Jelouſies</hi> betwixt one <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience-forcing</hi> King and an other: <hi>Kingdome &amp; Kingdome: Nation &amp; Nation:</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oit forceth them to draw their ſwords, and ſtandin continuall <hi>Defiance &amp; Defence</hi> for feare of <hi>mutuall Invaſion.</hi> Yea under a falſe <hi>Opinion of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Gods glory:</hi> by forcing others to their faith, they <hi>invade, aſſult and murther</hi> one an other, and yet both (deluded by this Seducer) thinke they doe God good ſervice, when alas it is all innocent blood that is ſhed: What was the maine cauſe ſo many Nations have been rent and divided in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and one againſt an other, and in their diviſions devoured one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of late dayes? What occaſioned the <hi>revolt</hi> of the <hi>Germaine Princes,</hi> from the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Auſtrea,</hi> of the <hi>Neitherlandess</hi> from the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> the <hi>bloody Maſkery</hi> in <hi>France?</hi> And amongſt our ſelves, what occaſioned the <hi>riſing</hi> of the <hi>Scots,</hi> the <hi>Rebellion</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and thoſe <hi>bloody diviſions</hi> in <hi>England</hi> but this diveliſh Spirit of binding the conſcience? One would compell the other to their faith, and force them from their owne, and that will not be borne, they had rather dye, then deny their faith; and therefore is it, that a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable party rebelleth, and in that Rebellion wallow in one an others blood, bume and deſtroy all before them, and yet both (as they ſuppoſe) <hi>ſight the Lords battell,</hi> while indeed the <hi>Divell</hi> beareth the greateſt ſhare, whoſe ſervants they are in that Quarrell owe as well as the other. Doth not the Holy Ghoſt make it it a ſpeaciall Marke of Antichriſt to force <hi>all both great and ſmall,</hi> &amp;c. and is it not the cauſe of the <hi>Womans flight</hi> inter the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121057:9"/>
from the preſence of the Dragon;</hi> the ſcattering of the Church into De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarts and ſecret places; the Death of the <hi>two Witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>wearing out of the Saints of the moſt High?</hi> How cometh the <hi>Woman</hi> on the <hi>ſcarlet coloured Beaſt drunke with the blood of the Saints, and with the blood of the Martyes of Jeſus, and all the blood of the Earth to be found in her,</hi> but by this diveliſh Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, even the <hi>Spirit of Divels. which goeth forth unto the Kings of the Earth, and of the whole world to provoake them to warre againſt the Saints;</hi> I meane, this <hi>binding of conſcience,</hi> and forceing conſormity, though never ſo much againſt knowledge and perſwat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of heart, which at this day is ſo hotly endeavoured, preached, and pleaded for by the <hi>proud, Prelaticall Presbytrie</hi> of this Land, who by their ſubtile inſinnations, and ſecret deluſions endeavour the infuſion thereof into the hearts of their Rulers, and to beget it as a principle of faith in the multitude: Should they poſſeſſe a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and Kingdome with this Spirit, that Parliament and Kingdom can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect peace and ſafety to continue; the fire may be ſmoohered for a time, but it wili breake out at laſt, as this Kingdome hath already fonnd by woefull experience, the blood of its Nobles and Commons, &amp;c. whereof <hi>my Lord,</hi> this <hi>infernall Feind</hi> (here araigned before your <hi>Honor,</hi> a Trator to his Majeſties Crown and Dignity, the Priviledges of Parliament, Rights, &amp; Lib: of the Subject, is the cauſe: Yea <hi>my Lord,</hi> he is <hi>Jakes on both ſides,</hi> in was he that occaſioned the feares and jealouſies betwixt his Majeſty and the two Houſes of Parliament, and unhappily drew them into the Feild of Blood, neither party would be oppreſſed in Conſcience, or deprived of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; this was one halfe of the Quarrell, and publikely profeſſed the main, though it may be <hi>Monarchie</hi> was the other halfe; and <hi>my Lord,</hi> he ſeduced the King into the <hi>North,</hi> and provoaked your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> unto <hi>Armes,</hi> and hath continued to this day firmely on both ſides, ſo that fall which ſide it will, he concludes to be <hi>Conquerer,</hi> and be eſtabliſhed abſolute <hi>Monarke,</hi> for he ſo deports himſelfe betwixt you both, that both may perſecute, and hitherto he hath too much prevailed with your <hi>Lordſhip:</hi> Therefore <hi>my Lord,</hi> if this <hi>vile Incendiary</hi> (here happily detected and <hi>araigned)</hi> be not cut off from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twikt you, there is no hopes of peace, till the ſword (and it may be ſamine, and peſtilence too) wreſtle it out to a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> on one ſide; and when all is done, yet peace will not, nor can poſſibly long endure; for where <hi>Perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is, there wil be <hi>heart burnings, envyings, emnlations,</hi> and <hi>murmurings,</hi> which at length will breake out into <hi>Commotions, Conſpiracies, Inſurrections</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions.</hi> And thus <hi>my Lord,</hi> I give place to what ſhall be further evidenced by the <hi>Witneſſes.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>GAFFAR <hi>CHRISTIAN ſtand up, what can you ſay for the</hi> King <hi>againſt the</hi> Priſoner <hi>at the</hi> Barre.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121057:10"/>
               <head>CHRISTIAN.</head>
               <p>My Lord, I have knowne this man by woefull Experience, well high 1644 yeares: and my brethren of old, the <hi>Prophets,</hi> bare witneſſe againſt him unto the day of my <hi>Nativity,</hi> that he was in their times the moſt <hi>Peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent</hi> Enemy to <hi>Mankind</hi> to <hi>God and all Goodneſſe,</hi> that ever was borne in to the World: and my Lord, I am able to prove his continuance in that cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Condicion</hi> oven unto this day: ſo that he hath lived and ſcaped the hands of Juſtice above 5660 yeares, and all his dayes hath been a <hi>Murderer and Butcher</hi> of good men, yea ſcarce any conſider it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, my Lord, this <hi>Priſoner,</hi> PERSECUTION for <hi>Conſcience, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Goſpell of none effect,</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Sincerity</hi> he ſetteth up <hi>Hyprocricy,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the <hi>Feare of God,</hi> he ſetteth up <hi>the Torrour of men:</hi> inſtead of the <hi>Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of the Word,</hi> he ſetteth up the <hi>Vſurpation of the Sword</hi> for my Lord, the compelling of men againſt their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> enforceth ſuch <hi>Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences</hi> and <hi>Impieties</hi> inevitably: Yea my Lord, of ſuch a Diveliſh Spirit is this <hi>Enemy</hi> of, as he exalteth himſelfe againſt the <hi>Mercy of</hi> God <hi>in</hi> Chriſt <hi>toward the Sonnes of men,</hi> to the very prevention thereof to Multitudes, and the tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of them head long without remorſe to the Divell: for they that are blind, they that are <hi>Tares,</hi> who knowes but they may ſee, may become Wheate heereafter: but if they be cut off, (as this mercileſſe <hi>Inhumane Miſcreant uſeth)</hi> for their blindneſſe, how ſhall they ſee? for <hi>(Iſa.</hi> 38. 19.) <hi>The Grave cannot praiſe thee, they that goe down into the Pit cannot hope for thy Truth. Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> may hereafter become faithfull <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 3. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9. 5. 6. <hi>Idolaters,</hi> true <hi>Worſhippers,</hi> no people of God, the people of God, as the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 9. <hi>&amp; ſome come at the firſt, third, ſixt, &amp; ſome not till the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leventh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Mat.</hi> 20. 6. but ſhould thoſe that are in their ſins till the II. houre be cut off becauſe <hi>they came no ſooner: they ſhould have been prevented</hi> from <hi>converſion,</hi> or <hi>coming</hi> at all, as godly King <hi>Edward</hi> moved by his <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Biſhops,</hi> to the burning of a godly <hi>Woman</hi> called <hi>John Butcher (Fox Act. Mon. p. 1784)</hi> anſwered, <hi>Will you have me ſend her quicke to the Divell in her errours.</hi> This is the ſervice this <hi>PERSECUTION</hi> doth, inſtead of building he deſtroyed, inſtead of ſaving he danneth, under the colours of Chriſt he figliteth for the Divell his Maſter.</p>
               <p>Thirdly <hi>my Lord,</hi> his nature is at direct emnity againſt the very command Chriſt gave unto the Apoſtles in the <hi>Generall Commiſſion: Goe teach all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. where <hi>teaching,</hi> not <hi>violent compulſion</hi> is <hi>conſtituted,</hi> and <hi>once for ever ordained</hi> she meanes and only way for <hi>converſion</hi> to the <hi>faith of Jeſus</hi> in <hi>all Nations:</hi> Now <hi>compulſion</hi> and <hi>perſwation</hi> all know are directly oppoſite, as much as to <hi>will</hi> and to <hi>nill;</hi> So that the command of the one by the Authority of the <hi>Father, the Son, and the Spirit,</hi> is a flat denyall of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121057:10"/>
other by the ſame Authority: For here <hi>(vec.</hi> 1920.) by full power of that Authority, <hi>Teaching</hi> is commanded; as, <hi>teach all Nations,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>teaching them to obſerve all things, what ever I have commanded,</hi> &amp;c. Therefore, <hi>all violence,</hi> as by <hi>monaces, threates, impriſonments, bodily puniſhments, ſpayling of goods,</hi> and ſuch like <hi>cruelties</hi> of <hi>this tyrant,</hi> is condemned in all <hi>Nations</hi> as a <hi>meanes for no Nation</hi> in the Adminiſtration of the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, my Lord, this <hi>Adverſaries</hi> practice and the Diſcipline of this <hi>old, envi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, malignant wretch</hi> here juſtly <hi>arigned</hi> before your <hi>Honour,</hi> is quite contrary to the Apoſtles in their Adminiſtration of the Goſpell; for they did r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuggeſt, or ſtirre up any Prince, or Majeſtrate (in whoſe hand is the <hi>compulſive civill power,)</hi> to force ſuch by violence of pepall I awes, Edicts, Ordinances, Impriſonments, or ſhe like, as would not ſuject unto their Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell: but on the contrary, gave up themſelves to ſeorgings, impriſonments, ſth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, &amp;c. which this <hi>Enemie</hi> occaſioned againſt them, for the promulgat on thereof. And the worſt that they did, or were commanded to doe, to ſuch as would not receive the Goſpell, was but to <hi>ſhake</hi> off the duſt from their feete, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Luke 10. 11. <hi>Acts</hi> 13. 51 which was nothing ſo ill, as this <hi>Beind's</hi> fire and faggot; burning, hanging, froning, ſtorging, impriſoning, &amp;c. whoſe nature hath ever been &amp; is alwayes verſant in ſuch crueltios; and yet my Lord, this ſpawne of Satin, this malitious Hyprocise, doth all under the vizour. of Religion, his wool feiſh nature is never ſeen abroad but in <hi>ſheeps clothing, in nomine Domini,</hi> he perpatrates, all his villany: So that <hi>my Lord,</hi> he is a moſt dangerous invererate <hi>Antichriſt</hi>'s and Archetraytour to his Majeſty (the <hi>King of Kings)</hi> his royall Crowne and Dignity, and in invadour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer of the juſt Liberies, the lives and, fortunes of his Majeſties leige people.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>my Lord,</hi> it is againſt the Law of Charity, <hi>not to do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>as we would be done unto:</hi> He that hangs a <hi>Jew,</hi> becauſe he will not be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> would be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a <hi>Jew</hi> ſhould reward him in the ſame kind, becauſe he will not be a <hi>Jew,</hi> though in equity he deſerve it. for <hi>innocent blood</hi> requireth <hi>blood.</hi> Yea <hi>my Lord,</hi> to forcemen and women againſt their conſciences is world then to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh the bodies of womena and Maides againſt their wills: Yea, it is beyond the <hi>Turkish</hi> cruelty, for though the Turkes force the bodies of Chriſtians and Strangers to ſlavery, yet they let their conſcience goe free: But our late Idol blood-ſucking Biſhops, and after them our ravenous <hi>Presbiters,</hi> as towardly <hi>younge Cubbes</hi> for beare not to force the conſciences of their freinds and neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; and impriſon them for walking after the light God hath given them: And <hi>my Lord,</hi> it is this <hi>Malefactaur</hi> which rendereth them ſo guilty: Yea <hi>my Lord,</hi> this <hi>Foule Spirit</hi> breathed into them at their <hi>Conſacration</hi> is not yet caſt out of them, <hi>which like a roaring Lion ſeeketh whome it may devoure:</hi> So that if your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> juſtice doe not ſpoedely interpoſe the <hi>bloody reſolves</hi> and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121057:11"/>
                  <hi>villanous intents</hi> of our new upſtart <hi>frisking Presbyters,</hi> we ſhall be all devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by thoſe greedy <hi>Synodian Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rants,</hi> which if you ſuffer, <hi>Wee</hi> then to your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> in the <hi>latter Day,</hi> for be aſſured, that all the miſeries, tortures, and torments they inflict upon us, will not only riſe up in judgment againſt them, but even againſt your <hi>Lordſhip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly <hi>my Lord,</hi> he uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>peth that to himſelfe, which Chriſt hath referred to the <hi>Laſt Day,</hi> to wit, to judge them that reject him, for <hi>John 12. 47. 48. If any man hear my words and beleive not, I judge him not, for I came not to judge the World, but to ſave the World: he that rejecteth me and receivetb not my words, hath one that judgeth him, the word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him at the laſt day. &amp; 1. Cor. 4. 5. Judge nothing before the time untill the Lord come and Mat. 7. 1. 2. Judge not leaſt yee be judged, for with what judgement yee judge, yee ſhall be judged</hi> &amp;c. and to theſe adde <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. 4. Therefore no man upon paine of judgement, muſt preſume to judge any in reſpect of Chriſt or his words, but muſt referre it to the laſt day, whoſe word ſhall judge him, and not <hi>Fire and Faggot, Hanging and Quartering, Impriſoning</hi> &amp;c. ſuch are incompetent Judges, for to this end Chriſt both died and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, that he might be Lord both of the dead and the living. <hi>Let us not therfore judge one another any more, but judge this rather, that no man put a ſtumbling Blocke as an occaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on of fall in his brothers way: for, Who art thou that judgeſt another mans ſervant? to his owne maſter he ſtandeth or falleth. Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
               <p>4. We are not equall Judges one over another in matters of Faith, <hi>Who is it that ſhall condemne? it is Chriſt that dyed:</hi> What is he that ſhall dare to execute Vengence for unbeleefe? <hi>He that is innocent let him throw the firſt ſtone.</hi> The Aſſembly (ſurely) will not plead Innocence, and if not, why are they ſo ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y to throw? <hi>Surely, Great is Diana of the Epheſians.</hi> Yet Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> a man but newly <hi>Metamorphoſed</hi> by a figure which we Rhetoricians call METONOMIA BENEFICII from <hi>Epiſcopallity</hi> to <hi>Preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ytery:</hi> upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what they would doe with Anabaptiſts, Antinomians &amp;c. tells us, <hi>That they will not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ddle with their</hi> Conſciences, <hi>but with their</hi> Bodyes <hi>and</hi> Eſtates. Truly if this be the drift, they are even <hi>leapt out of the Frying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> into the Fire.</hi> If they be fallen, this is not to reſtore them with the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of meeknes. But <hi>my Lord,</hi> Juſtice upon this Malefactour would cure the Synodians of that Diſeaſe, for <hi>Patience per force is a Medicine for a madde Dogge.</hi> And thus <hi>my Lord,</hi> your Honour hath my Teſtimony of this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactour.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>GAFFAR MARTYRS, What can you ſay for the King againſt the <hi>Priſoner</hi> at the Barre?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>MARTYRS.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord,</hi> Had not my <hi>life been hid in Jeſus Chriſt, who is God of the living,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121057:11"/>
and not of the dead,</hi> for though dead in the grave, yet I live unto him, to be raiſed and revived at the <hi>laſt day;</hi> or could the arme of fleſh ſuppreſſe the <hi>cry of blood,</hi> my witneſſe would have been diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>abled: for this Malefacteur PERSECUTION perſecuted me even to the death; ſo that my voyce is no other then the <hi>cry of blood,</hi> even of the Prophets and Martyrs of Jeſus, that you heare; for <hi>my Lord,</hi> ſuch hath been his cruelty to me to ſuppreſſe my Teſtimony againſt him while I was living, that all the tortures and tormen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wit and malice could invent, he with his <hi>blood-thirſty Clergy</hi> deviſed againſt, and executed upon me, whereby I was moſt baberouſly murthered; ſo that <hi>my Lord,</hi> I have no other voyce left me, then that of <hi>blood, ſplit for the Word of God and the teſtimony of Jeſus, crying with a loud voyce, how long O Lord ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and true doſt thou not avenge our blood?</hi> I could enlarge my ſelfe into a Sea of blood againſt him, diſcover him drunken with the blood of the Saints and Martyres of Jeſus: yea <hi>my Lord,</hi> Articles of all manner of impiety a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and all goodneſſe, Treaſons, Rebellions, &amp;c. I could exhibite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, but my faithfull brother, that pore deſpiſed CHRISTIAN, hath moſt juſtly witneſſed abundantly againſt him: And there is yet an other faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Witneſſe to give in his <hi>Evidence,</hi> Gaffar <hi>LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE,</hi> who I know, is thoroughly furniſhed with matters of higheſt concernement againſt him, to whoſe juſt <hi>Evidence</hi> I ſhall give place.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>Gaffar <hi>LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE, what can you ſay for the King againſt the Priſoner at the Barre?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſoner.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord,</hi> before he proceed, be pleaſed to heare the juſt excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Sir <hi>Symon Synod</hi> and Sir <hi>John Presbyter</hi> after their ſo long and ſerious <hi>conſultation</hi> have deviſed and contrived, why his Teſtimony ſhould not be heard, as an unſit Witneſſe in ſuch a caſe as this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Juſtice Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord, if Baal be God, let him plead for himſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>And reaſon good: For the judgment of this Court is not to be ſwayed by favour, affection, humour of multitudes, or the like, but by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and equity it ſelfe: Wherefore for the more free and juſt proceding here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Court <hi>Ordaineth</hi> and <hi>Proclameth</hi> freedome for both ſides, one as well as the other, whether <hi>Presbyterian Tormentoi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> or <hi>Independant Sufferers</hi> to give in their grounds and reaſons to the <hi>Sentence</hi> of this Court, whether LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE be tollerable, and his Evidence to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. Wherefore Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> if you have any thing why this mans <hi>witneſſe</hi> may be di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nabled, you have liberty to ſpeake.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>Sir SYMON SYNOD.</head>
               <p>My Lord, <hi>this fellow</hi> LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a Free-willer, a looſe Libectine, one that opens a gate to all manner of prophanes, in what</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121057:12"/>
                  <hi>or</hi> State <hi>ſoever he gets intertainement, a man of all Religions and of no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, a compound of all hereſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, ſciſme, and faction; a preſtelent enemie to Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Conformity, our late</hi> Solemne League and Covenant, <hi>a Tratour to your late</hi> ſacred and bleſſed Ordinance for Tythes, a worke of Superarrogation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>a</hi> Confuter <hi>of our mighty Champions Mr.</hi> Priune, Edwards, <hi>&amp;c. He is for no</hi> Reformation, <hi>but ſtrives to fruſtrate all my endeavours, and the pious ends of the reſt of my holy brethren of the</hi> Tribe of Lev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for the advancement of the Church God,</hi> the Clergie of the Land, <hi>with eccleſiaſticall Revennue, and power coercive to curbe oppoſition, and force</hi> Reformation to Presbyterian Governement: <hi>yea</hi> my Lord, <hi>this is he that would reduce the Nationall Reformation of this Kingdome, ſo much endeavoured by your</hi> Lordſhip, <hi>even to open looſenſſe, every man to be of what Religion he li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, every mecannioke illiterate fellow to turne</hi> Preacher, <hi>and be as good as their</hi> Miniſter, <hi>no diſtinction made betwixt the</hi> Clergie <hi>and the</hi> Laity, <hi>our</hi> Canonicall Coates, Girdles, long Cloakes <hi>and</hi> Blacke Gowno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>made a diriſion, a taunt, and a curſe, as ominous as Lawne ſleeves and as hatefull as a Miter, our</hi> holy Tythes, <hi>as of</hi> Lambe, Pigge, Gooſe, <hi>&amp;c. be turned into</hi> voluntary Contribution, <hi>oh inſufferable ſacraledge!</hi> from the good will of the people good Lord preſerve us: <hi>yea</hi> my Lord, <hi>the</hi> upper hand <hi>in publike places,</hi> (the Clergies delight) <hi>as, in</hi> ſtreets, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> feaſts, &amp;c. be deny'd us, <hi>the reverent eſtimation of our</hi> Coate <hi>be paſt either</hi> Cap, Congue, or Curtſey, <hi>no difference betwixt the</hi> Black Caſſocke <hi>and the</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Jacket, <hi>and all our good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyfat</hi> Benefices <hi>turnd to the labour of our hands,</hi> (alas my Lord, we were never brought up to labour, we cannot digge, and to begge we are aſham'd) <hi>our</hi> deluſions, falſe Gloſſes, Sophiſtications, <hi>and</hi> godly pretonces <hi>be detected, and divulged, and ſo all things that are dainty and goodly to depart from us:</hi> alas, alas my Lord! <hi>this will undoe the</hi> Clergie <hi>quite, we may leave our</hi> Callings, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd learne new</hi> Trades, <hi>if we turne</hi> Coblers, Tinkers, <hi>and</hi> Weavers <hi>we may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hance get conſtant worke, if not, now and then a</hi> job of preaching <hi>amongſt the people;</hi> Conſider my Lord, <hi>it will put out the</hi> two eyes of the Kingdome: <hi>Much more I could ſay, but I ſhall give way to my Son</hi> Sir John, <hi>who by your Lordſhips favour ſhall further informe this</hi> Court <hi>in the defence of this</hi> Priſoner.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir Symon, this being a buſines of high concernment, either what you or your <hi>Sir John,</hi> or what any man elſe can ſay in the behalfe of his Majeſty concerning the Priſoner, this Court freely permitteth, yea com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth Information thereof.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clar.</speaker>
                  <p>Call Sir John Prosbyter, ſonne to Sir Symon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</speaker>
                  <p>Magus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir John Presbyter ſonne to Sir Symon come into the Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir John your Father hath informed us, that you have matter of exception againſt LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE, if you have the mercy of the Court permiteeth the Priſoner the benefit thereof.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121057:12"/>
               <head>Sir <hi>JOHN PRESBYTER</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord,</hi> My Reaſons againſt LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE, why both himſelfe and his <hi>Evidence</hi> is to be rejected, are theſe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe I ſuppoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> muſt needs be granted, that the Majeſtrate is <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Edwards Antipol. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g.</hi> 280.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſtos a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vindex vtriuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Tabulae,</hi> (as is confeſſed by all Orthodox Divines) that the care of Religion belongs to him: And becauſe <hi>Auſtin</hi> and other Divines on <hi>Pſal</hi> 2. 10. 11. and on <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t.</hi> 17. 19. give unto Mageſtrates that power. Ergo,</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>States-men muſt weare Bells about their neckes, becauſe antient Divines ſay Kings are but Packe-horſes to the Clergie.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Becauſe in this Kingdome the Reformation in Worſhip, Government, &amp;c. which ſhalbe ſetled and eſtabliſhed by your Lordſhip is judged and taken <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 281.</note> for granted by you to be according to the mind of Chriſt; elſe why hath your Lordſhip called ſo many able, godly, and learned Divines (of us) to conſult with for that purpoſe? and why elſe will you eſtabliſh it, if there be any other more agreable to the Word? Ergo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Synod is guided by the Holy Ghoſt ſent in a Cloake-bag from Scotland, as of old from Rome to the Councell of Trent,</hi> Goncil. Trent l. 6 p. 497.]</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Becauſe it is againſt the ſolemne League and Covenant for Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, taken by the Parliament and Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag. 282. &amp;</hi> 283.</note> ſo cannot be condeſcended to in <hi>England</hi> without the breach of that Oath and Covenant: So that all <hi>Apollogie</hi> and motion for Toleration comes too late, the dore is ſhut againſt it, the Kingdomes hands are bound, ſo that if a Toleration were not in it ſelfe unlawfull, and againſt the duty of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtrate, yet now becauſe of the Oath and Covenant 'tis unlawfull; ſo that whatſoever might have been granted before, cannot be now, leaſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſhould be guilty <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>efore God of Covenant breaking. Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Becauſe the</hi> Aſſembly <hi>bath ſadled the Parliament, it is unlawfull for the</hi> Presbyters <hi>to goe a foote.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Perſecution was unlawfull when the Preiſts were perſecuted, but now it is lawfull they perſecute.</hi> Ergo, <hi>Toleration was lawfull, and the duty of the Majeſtrate when the power was in the hands of the Biſhops, but now the Presbyters are crowding into S.</hi> Peters Chaire, <hi>the Parliament is bound to compell all men to the Decrees of the Aſſembly, as that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, and deſperate Incendiary</hi> Mr. Edwards <hi>boldly and openly affirmeth, an Aſſertion able to divide the Kingdome in twenty peeces.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. Becauſe it is againſt the greateſt lights in the Church both antient and <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 281.</note> moderne, as <hi>Aguſtine, Ambroſe, Calvine, Phillip Melancton, Zanchius, Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus, Bullinger,</hi> likewiſe the judgement of the Divines of <hi>New England</hi> are
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121057:13"/>
againſt the Toleration of any Church Governement and way but one, they will not ſuffer <hi>Browniſts, Anabaptiſts,</hi> &amp;c. Mr. <hi>Cotton</hi> the greateſt Divine in <hi>New England,</hi> and a precious man, is againſt Toleration, and holds that men may be puniſhed for their Conſciences, as will appeare by his Letter to Mr. <hi>Williams.</hi> Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Presbyterian Governement is unlawfull, becauſe Mr.</hi> Cotton <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnes it in his Booke intituled,</hi> The Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven.]</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Becauſe at this time for want of ſetled Governement, people being left to ſo great liberty, multitudes are fallen, and doe daily to <hi>Antinomianiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 289.</note> 
                     <hi>Anabaptiſme, Independancy,</hi> yea to deny the <hi>Immortality of the ſoule:</hi> Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>One</hi> Anabaptiſt, Independant, <hi>or the like, that can render a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for what he holds, is better then ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ven</hi> Presbyters <hi>that conclude from ſuch bald Premiſes, Pro.</hi> 26. 16.] [Here the Authour of that Booke, intituled, <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns Mortality,</hi> deſires Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> with thoſe that are ſo invective againſt it in their Pulpits that they would ceaſe their railing at it there, and come forth in Print againſt it; for the thing being ſo rare, ſo litle queſtioned, and the contrary ſo generally concluded as a principle of faith, any <hi>bumbaſt-ſtuffe</hi> will paſſe there for authentike with the people without tryall, but if it be put forth to publike vew, it muſt expect an encounter by one or other, and therein the Authour of that Booke obſerveth the policie of his Presbyterian Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries to maintaine their repute with the people, in being ſo haſty in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit and ſo ſlow to the Preſſe.]</p>
                  <p n="6">6. <hi>Independants,</hi> and all kind of <hi>Sectaries</hi> as long as they have their liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <note place="margin">pag. ibid.</note> ſnuffe up the wind, and will not hearken to any way whereby they may receive ſatisfaction; but if once the Majeſtrate declares, and by Lawes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes one way of Church Worſhip, it may be they will heare reaſon. Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It ſeemes the Presbyters till then can render them none, for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orce of that Argument li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s in</hi> take him Goaler. Ergo, <hi>If once the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtrate declares, and by Lawes concludes all the fat Benefices of the Kingdome upon</hi> Independancie, <hi>then it may be the</hi> Presbyters <hi>will beare reaſon, and turne</hi> Independants.]</p>
                  <p n="7">7. <hi>Independancie</hi> hath ever been from the firſt to the laſt, a Fountaine of evill, roote of bitternes, diviſions, &amp;c. as the Hiſtories of the Anabaptiſts (the <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 394.</note> higheſt forme of <hi>Independancy,</hi> and Church way) declare, in reſpect of the evils they fell into, and the miſcheifes they brought upon <hi>Germany,</hi> and how God curſed and ſcattered them. Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If the King conquer, the Parliament wilbe Traytours to poſterity by Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nicle; for who writ the Hiſtories of the Anabaptiſts but their Enemies?]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. <hi>My Lord,</hi> becauſethe Presbyterian way hath been countenanced from <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 29<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Heaven, and bleſſed from ſorts of ſects, &amp;c. and that for almoſt an hundered yeares: Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121057:13"/>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Both Papall and Epiſcopall is better then Presbyterian, for they are, and have been more vniforme, and have continued many hundred yeares lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then Presbyterian, and were long before Presbytrie was thought on: for alas, it was but a ſhift at a pinch the Divell made, when neither of the other would ſerve his turne; and ſo came up Presbytrie, but what good the Divell will have on't I know not; for</hi> who knowes the lucke of a Iouſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Curre, he may prove a good Dog?]</p>
                  <p n="9">9. <hi>My Lord,</hi> If Toleration of Government though not of Doctrine <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 301.</note> ſhould be granted, then the ſimple Anabaptiſts, and that ſimple ſort called <hi>Dippers</hi> will come in too, ſaying, that Baptiſme at ſuch an age, and Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing in Rivers by <hi>Dipping</hi> are but matters of order and time: Ergo,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that deſembleth hatred with lying lips, and he that inventeth ſlander is a foole, Pro.</hi> 10. 18.]</p>
                  <p>Wherefore I humbly beſeech your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> ſeriouſly to conſider the depth <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 303.</note> of Satan in this Deſigne, of Toleration, how this is now his laſt Plot and Deſigne, and by it would undermine and fruſtrate the whole worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, tis his Maſter peece for <hi>England.</hi> I am confident if the Divell <note place="margin">
                        <hi>pag.</hi> 304.</note> had his choyce. whether the Hierarchie, Ceremonies, and Liturgie ſhould be eſtabliſhed in this Kingdome, or a Toleration granted, he would chuſe and preferre a Toleration before them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>[J. Human.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That is of Presbyterian Compulſion, becauſe Epiſcopall in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>is worne out of Date:</hi> Mr. Edwards <hi>knowes the Divell is not ſo ſimple, to chuſe Hierarchie, Ceremonies, &amp;c. where their deceit is detected, hated, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, it ſeemes be's better acquainted with him then ſo, the next time he writes, we ſhall have more of the Divels mind, but it is likely he'll have finiſhed his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne firſt, and then it may be,</hi> Mr. Edwrads <hi>will tell us, that the Divell is better perſwaded of Presbytrie (his laſt ſhift) then ever he was of Epiſcopacie, he will be ſo ſerviceable to him therein, for if</hi> Mr. Edwards <hi>and the Divell be not decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, he intends with it to devoure, breake in peeces, and ſtampe the reſidue the Hierarchie hath left under his feete, ſo to weare out the Saints of the moſt High.]</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And thus <hi>my Lord,</hi> you have, my Reaſons, why this fellow <hi>LIBERTY-OF CONSCIENCE,</hi> is not to have admittance within the verge of this Kingdom, much leſſe to enter thus into the bowels of this Court to give in Evidence to be proceeded on upon the life and death of this holy man, Mr. <hi>PERSECU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lib. Conſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, <hi>Sir John<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> a pritty forward child, that can pratle thus before he have his teeth; thy ſay he hath been breeding of teeth ever ſince the the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> were in conſultation; ſurely they'll be huge, long, boariſh tuskes when they come <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut; ſhould your Lordſhip but cauſe his mouth to be opened, you might ſee <hi>great iron teeth</hi> lie in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ready to <hi>cut,</hi> he wants nothing but a <hi>Parliament Corrall</hi> to whet them with all:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121057:14"/>
but <hi>my Lord,</hi> were he mine, I would knock out his braines with an <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Hammer,</hi> to prevent the groweth of ſuch teeth, for <hi>Daniell</hi> tels us the nature of <hi>great iron teeth.</hi> Now whereas <hi>my Lord,</hi> he excepteth againſt my witneſſe, I humbly conceive, the equity of this Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> cannot receive his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt me in the juſtification of this Butcher and murtherer of good men, ſeeing himſelfe is a mercileſſe inhumane Butcher, the ſon of a Butcher, yea <hi>my Lord,</hi> his Grand-father and Great-Grand-father were Butchers; for whereas <hi>my Lord,</hi> he hath acquired the name of <hi>Sir John Presbyter,</hi> in truth he is a Preiſt, the ſon of a Biſhop, Grand-child to the Pope, and the Divell is his Great-Grand-father, all murtherers and Butchers of Gods people. Therefore <hi>good my Lord</hi> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not mine <hi>Evidence</hi> be thus unjuſtly diſinabled.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE, you are ſworne for the King, to give in your <hi>Evidence</hi> in his Majeſties behalfe againſt the Priſoner at the Bar; and the <hi>challenge</hi> againſt you being ſuch as may be dispenc'd with, you are to proceed in your <hi>Evidence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <head>LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Lord,</hi> To what the former <hi>Evidence</hi> have teſtified I ſhall with brevity adde, that this Malefactour PERSECUTION deſtroyeth the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent with the wicked, contrary to the comma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d of Chriſt, <hi>Mat. 13. 30. let the tares and the wheat grow together untill the harveſt,</hi> from which <hi>Parable</hi> appeareth, that the <hi>Kingdome of heaven</hi> or <hi>Chriſts</hi> Government over the whole world doth ſtrictly charge his <hi>ſervants,</hi> the Kings and Rulers of the Earth (for <hi>by him Kings raigne)</hi> to ſuffer <hi>tares;</hi> Turkes, Jewes, Pagans, and Infidels, as well as Chriſtians to <hi>grow</hi> or live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ogether in the <hi>Feild</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> their Dominions untill the <hi>Day of harveſt,</hi> or deſolution of all things, and not plucke them up, becauſe they are <hi>Tares, Turkes, Jewes, Pagans, &amp;c.</hi> leaſt they plucke up ſuch as may become as the <hi>Pillars of Solomon</hi> in the Houſe of God, even glorious witneſſes of Jeſus Chriſt: What greater Rebellion therefore can there be by thoſe <hi>Servants</hi> to the <hi>Houſholder,</hi> then to <hi>plucke up the tares from the wheat?</hi> As their Office brings all under their Dominions, ſo it is to preſerve all in their Dominions, that <hi>tares</hi> and <hi>wheate,</hi> Infidell and Beleiver may <hi>grow</hi> and live peaceably together in civill cohabitation, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, &amp;c. in their Dominions untill the <hi>Harveſt,</hi> or end of all things, when the <hi>Lord of the Harveſt</hi> ſhall <hi>ſeperate the tares from the wheat,</hi> with <hi>come ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bleſſed, goe yee curſed, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly <hi>my Lord,</hi> he depriveth the <hi>Jewes</hi> (as much as in him lieth) of their geliverance according to the Covenant God made with their Fathers from this their Captivity, notwithſtanding the wrath of the Lord threatned againſt them, that ſhall evill entreat them th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rein, <hi>Zach. 2. 8. Eſa.</hi> 54. 15. 17.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121057:14"/>
                  <hi>cap.</hi> 51. 22. 23. for <hi>my Lord,</hi> he hath made the name of a <hi>Jew</hi> as hatefull as <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das;</hi> yea, his nature is not to leave a man of them to piſſe againſt the wall. Now <hi>my Lord,</hi> though the <hi>Jewes</hi> are led captive by the <hi>Gentiles</hi> under the time of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and though the <hi>naturall branches are broaken off,</hi> and the Heathen <hi>grafted in,</hi> yet ſtill <hi>they are beloved for their Fathers ſakes, Rom.</hi> 11. 28. and are not to be perſecuted for their infidelity, for <hi>he that toucheth them, toucheth the apple of Gods eye:</hi> What though they are <hi>ſtumbled? ſhall we boaſt our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them?</hi> God forbid; for <hi>if wee that are wild by nature, be grafed contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to nature into the good Olive Tree, how much more ſhall they which are naturall branches be grafted into their owne Olive Tree againe?</hi> Therefore the Apoſtle <hi>would not have us ignorant of this Myſtery, that blindneſſe in part is hapned to Iſrael untill the fulneſſe of the Gentiles be come in, and all Iſrael ſhalbe ſaved, Rom.</hi> 11. 25. 26. compared to <hi>Iſa. 49. 22. 23. Deut. 30. 1. 2. 4. 5. Amos</hi> 9. 14. 15. Now what hindereth their ſalvation and deliverance ſo much as perſecution, for they are even led captive by PERSECUTION, and made ſlaves to him even to this day? And how ſhall they beleive, if they ſhall have no time given them to beleive? this <hi>diveliſh Spirit</hi> gives them not a minute, he will not ſuffer a Jew to live amongſt the Chriſtians, or come neare him: what hopes then is there the Jewes ſhould be converted, where this Tyrant is in force? Shall we that have received <hi>vantage</hi> by their <hi>rejection,</hi> thus recompence them with ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny? our <hi>Lord</hi> whome they ſlew, would not have them ſlaven, but they are beloved of him, and himſelfe will be their Deliveror, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 26. 27. 28. yes this Incendiary hath cauſed our Kings, and our Rulers, our Biſhops and our preiſts not to ſuffer a Jew by authority to live amongſt them; how then can we complaine of the vengance that is at this time upon us &amp; our children, that have been ſo cruell, ſo hatefull, ſo bloody minded to them and their children? we have given them the <hi>cup of trembling,</hi> ſurely we muſt <hi>taſt of the dregges:</hi> Hearken therefore no longer to thoſe which teach this bloody doctrine of perſecution, for neither they, their <hi>preachings, faſtings, weepings long prayres,</hi> &amp;c. can deliver in the day of <hi>diſtreſſe,</hi> as long as ye perſecute: <hi>Behold, yee faſt for ſtrife and debate, and to ſmite with the</hi> Presbyterian <hi>fiſt of wickedneſſe; but this is the Faſt which the Lord hath choſen, to undoe the heavy burthen, and to let the oppreſſed goe free, and that yee breake every yoake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly <hi>my Lord,</hi> He is a murtherer of Kings and Princes, &amp;c. for the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of <hi>heriticke Princes</hi> is the naturall brat of this diveliſh Spirit; for from this ground, <hi>that the contrary minded are to be forced,</hi> the Papiſts juſtifie the murthering of <hi>Herticks,</hi> making all <hi>Heretickes</hi> which ſeperate from them; for that Religion that is bottomed on this <hi>principle,</hi> that <hi>all muſt be forced, will they, nill they,</hi> where it cannot <hi>force,</hi> muſt murther: ſo cometh it to paſſe, ſo many Kings have been <hi>murthered,</hi> by the Papiſts, becauſe caſting of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh yoake,</hi> they free themſelves from their power of forcing, therefore the
<pb facs="tcp:121057:15"/>
Papiſts to make good their coercive principle, betake themſelves <hi>privately to murther ſuch Princes,</hi> to prevent a countermanding power, and keep all in their <hi>catholicke ſubjection;</hi> ſo that ſuch as would have <hi>all forced,</hi> where they connot <hi>force,</hi> is to be feared, will <hi>privately murther:</hi> Therefore it is dangerous for a King <hi>to truſt his perſon with ſuch men,</hi> for if the King ſhould <hi>change his Religion,</hi> to one oppoſite to theirs, who knowes, thoſe men will not doe as their principle leads them, even <hi>murther their Prince;</hi> but on the contrary, that <hi>Religion</hi> that is grounded on the principle of <hi>meekeneſſe patience, and long ſufferance, inſtructing the contrary minded,</hi> and utterly conteſting againſt all <hi>compulſion,</hi> cannot in the leaſt meaſure adminiſter any feare or danger unto <hi>Princes of their perſons,</hi> be of what <hi>Religion they will,</hi> for be they of any <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> or of no <hi>Religion,</hi> for <hi>matter of violence</hi> it is <hi>all one</hi> to the Spirit of meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for its nature is only to perſwade, not to compell; if by faire meanes it cannot prevai'e, it hath done, committing the iſſue to God.</p>
               <p>Fourthly <hi>my Lord,</hi> He is an utter enemy to all ſpirituall knowledge, a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer of its encreaſe and groweth; for no man knoweth but in part, and what wee know, we receive it by degrees, now a litle, and them a litle; he that knowes the moſt, was once as ignorant as he that knowes the leaſt; nay, is it not frequent amongſt us, that the thing that we judged hereſie we now beleive is orthodox; now can ſuch thinke themſelves were worthy to beene perſecuted in, and for that their ignorance? they cannot ſure be of that mind; ſuch therefore cannot condemne, impriſon, or hang the ignorant, or ſuch as diſcover or oppoſe their ignorance, but in that they condemne themſelves, ſinne againſt nature and their own knowledge: The <hi>twelve at Epheſus</hi> that had not ſo much as heard <hi>whether there were a Holy Ghoſt or no,</hi> if they had been ſo evilly uſed by <hi>Paul</hi> when he heard it, how ſhould they ſpake with tongues, and prophoſied? yet we ſee how common a thing it is, if we know not, nor beleive ſo much as the multitude knoweth or beleiveth, or the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the <hi>Presbycrean Church</hi> requireth, we muſt be perſecuted; and if our knowledge goe beyond them, that we proteſt againſt their errours, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to informe them better, wee muſt taſt of the ſame ſauee too, ſo that wee muſt know nor beleive neither more nor leſſe then they, but muſt beleive juſt as they beleive, or elſe be perſecuted; as if a Statute ſhould be enacted, that an <hi>Image</hi> ſhould be made, and all that were higher or lower then the <hi>Image</hi> ſhould be hanged: By this we may ſee, what an unreaſonable thing it is evil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to entroat ſuch as we judge ignorant and erroneous, or all to be erronious and hereticall that we underſtand not our ſelves: What ſhall we ſay then of ſuch <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that of rationall creatures would teach us to be thus nnrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable? <hi>their end is deſtinction, their belly, them God, they ſerve the</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>but for their owne bellyes, and by good words and faire ſpeeches deceive the ſimple:</hi> Theſe uphold the accurſed Doctrine of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> leaſt liberty of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121057:15"/>
                  <hi>printing, writing, teaching,</hi> ſhould diſcover their deceipts, and they be diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herited of their <hi>Fathers Inheritance;</hi> their intents are plaine to him that hath but halfe an eye to ſee, they'l not doe much, only change the title, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was <hi>Epiſcopal Prelacy,</hi> it ſhall be now but <hi>Preiſtly</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian Prelay,</hi> ſo that, he that lives but a ſmall time ſhall ſurely ſee a <hi>Presbyter</hi> as fat as ever was a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> thoſe are enemies to all knowledge, that is either too ſhort or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond their bellyes, therefore is it, that all heads muſt be made even with the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> none <hi>higher</hi> nor none <hi>lower,</hi> juſt as <hi>tall,</hi> and no <hi>taller, he that is too ſhort muſt be ſtretched out, and he that is too long muſt be pared even,</hi> leaſt they ſhould miſſe of their Prayers, <hi>give us this day our dayly tythes,</hi> that the <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine proverbe</hi> might be fulfilled, <hi>phophen geizegkeite, Gattes barmchartzegkite, were his in ebekeite,</hi> the coveteouſneſſe of the Preints and the mercy of God en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure for ever; I would exhort them to be otherwiſe minded, but that I know, <hi>venter non habet aures,</hi> the belly hath no eares.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Priſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, <hi>I beſeech you heare me after this tedious Accuſation, it is falſe and malitious, as by ſound reaſon, and Perſonages of Honour</hi> I <hi>ſhall clearly evidence: Firſt</hi> my Lord, <hi>as for</hi> GODS VENGANCE <hi>my</hi> Proſecutour, <hi>both the</hi> Juries, <hi>with divers others, together with the witneſſes, enforced him to proſecute me, and I know not by what pretence they procured</hi> GODS VENGANCE <hi>againſt me; for</hi> my Lord, <hi>I am innocent, and ever have been from my Cradle from ſuch and ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous accuſation, as is laid to my charge: And for that fellow, that pretends he hath knowne me ſince the comeing of Chriſt, he is a man of no reputation, without habitation, a beggerly fellow, arunagate, a looſe fellow, he ſtayes in no place, keeps no hospitallity, blaſpheameth that moſt divine, Leviticall, ever to adored</hi> Ordinance for Tythes, <hi>and counteth it as an unholy thing, paies none where he lives, but ſharkes here and there, where he can ſkufle in his head, runnes from houſe to houſe, to delude ſimple women, who are ever learning, and never learned, and whereas he ſaith, his name is CHRISTIAN, his name is not CHRISTIAN, neither is he of the generation of Chriſtianity, but a moſt factious diſſembling Anabaptiſt, a Tub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preacher, and no chriſtian, as</hi> Sir Symon, Sir John, <hi>and divers other reverend, and honourable</hi> perſons <hi>here preſent can</hi> witneſſe: <hi>As for</hi> Gaffar Martyrs, <hi>he is</hi> as a ſounding braſſe and tinckling Cymball, who though he giveth up his body to be burnt, himſelfe is but a caſtaway, <hi>and this I am able to make good unto your</hi> Honour, <hi>by the moſt grave, and ſolid judgment of all the reverend Divines,</hi> the Clergie of Chriſtendome: <hi>Therefore my Lord, it much mattereth not, what his Evidence is, it being but the malice of an Hereticke: And as for LIBERTY OF CONSCIENCE,</hi> Sir Symon, <hi>and that bleſſed babe, his Sonne</hi> Sir John, <hi>(Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from his mothers wombe, the</hi> Synodian Whore of Bibylon,) <hi>hath informed your</hi> Honour <hi>of the unworthyneſſe of his witneſſe.</hi> My Lord, <hi>I deſire</hi> Sir Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>may ſpeake in my defence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir <hi>Symon.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, this Gentleman here arraigned, is altogether inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121057:16"/>
from this accuſation, I have had antient familiarity with him, a dayly ſociety hath paſt betwixt us, and I never could find any ſuch thing in him, and my Lord, here is Mr. <hi>Pontificall Revennue,</hi> Mr. <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Supremacy,</hi> Mr. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <hi>tionall Conformity,</hi> Mr. <hi>Rude Multitude,</hi> Mr. <hi>Scotch Government,</hi> and mine on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sonne, <hi>Sir John Presbyter,</hi> all to witnes his innocency from this Accuſation: And if your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> make any ſcruple hereof, that learned Gentleman, <hi>Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as Conformity, of Lincolns Inne Eſq.</hi> can thorughly reſolve you, <hi>both by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Texts, Preſidents of all ſorts, and the conſiant interrupted practiſes, examples, of the moſt eminent Emperours, Princes, Councels, Parliaments,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lib. Conſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, the <hi>Defendant</hi> ſmels of a <hi>fat Benefice;</hi> ſee, ſee, his pockets are full of <hi>Presbyterian Steeples,</hi> the <hi>Spires</hi> ſticke under his <hi>Girdle: ha, ha, hah;</hi> inſtead of <hi>Weather-cocks,</hi> every <hi>Spire</hi> hath got a <hi>Blacke</hi> Boxe upon it. and in it the pure and immaculate <hi>Ordinance for Tythes, Oblations,</hi> &amp;c. Sure ſhortly, inſtead of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ron,</hi> and the <hi>Two Tables,</hi> we ſhall have Sir <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and Sir <hi>John</hi> holding the <hi>late ſolemne League and Covenant,</hi> and that demure, ſpotleſſe, pritty, lovely, ſacred, divine, devout, and holy <hi>Ordinance for Tythes</hi> (the <hi>Two Tables</hi> of our new <hi>Presbyterian Goſpell)</hi> painted upon all the Churches in <hi>England.</hi> Oh brave Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> the <hi>Bels</hi> in your pocket chime <hi>all-in</hi> while ours chime <hi>all-out:</hi> I pray you give us a <hi>Funerall Homile</hi> for your friend here before he <hi>depart,</hi> here's <hi>twenty ſhillings</hi> for your paines, you know 'tis ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craledg to bring downe the price, <hi>As it was in the beginning, is now, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall be, world without end. Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Make way there for the Jurie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Jurie withdraw, and thus fall into debate about their verdict.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Creation.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, from the <hi>Evidence</hi> of the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> againſt PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SECUTION, I clearely perceive, that he is of ſo diveliſh and unnaturall diſpoſition, as is not computible with the workes of the Creation, all creaturs of a kind aſſociate, feed, and converſe together, there is a publicke freedome of all kinds amongſt themſelves, the <hi>Oxe,</hi> the <hi>Aſſe,</hi> the <hi>Sheep,</hi> and all ſorts of <hi>Cattell;</hi> the <hi>Dove,</hi> the <hi>Sparrow,</hi> and all kinds of <hi>Birds</hi> have a State harmony, a publike Toleration, generall Concord and unity among themſelves in their ſeverall kinds: but this <hi>Malefactour</hi> as from the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> is evident, unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallizes <hi>man-kind</hi> above all kinds of Creatures, that where he rules, no peace publike, or private; no freedome, rights, or liberty either civil or ſpirituall; no ſociety, cohabitation, or concord Nationall nor Domeſticke can poſſibly be amongſt men, but <hi>envying, hatred, emulation, baniſhment,</hi> &amp;c. Wherefore, from the conſideration hereof, and of what the Witneſſes have given in, to me he appeareth <hi>guilty,</hi> what ſay you Mr. <hi>Goſpell?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Goſp.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> Whereas it is by Sir <hi>John</hi> and ſuch like urged, that the Kings of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> have equall power with the Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that their ſupremacy was but for a time, <hi>untill Shiloh came,</hi> and no
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121057:16"/>
longer, <hi>to whome then the gathering of the people ſhould be; he came to take away the Firſt, that he might eſtabliſh the Second, being made Mediatour of a better Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, eſtabliſhed on better promiſes,</hi> the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and the guift of eternall life: <hi>But he that deſpiſed Moſes Laws, dyed without mercy under two or three witneſſes.</hi> The old Covenant was over the <hi>Old man,</hi> and its Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation or puniſhment was over the <hi>Old man,</hi> to wit, this corruptable fallen State of Mortallity, and therefore they executed death upon the tranſgreſſors thereof. The <hi>New Covenant</hi> is over the <hi>New man,</hi> to wit, the <hi>Spirit</hi> that ſhall be raiſed out of this corruptable at the <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> therefore hath it the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſins,</hi> and <hi>eternall life;</hi> the penalty of that, temporall death, the death of the <hi>Old</hi> or <hi>earthly man</hi> in this life; the penalty of this, <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death,</hi> the death of the <hi>New</hi> or <hi>ſpirituall man</hi> in the life to come; wee are <hi>New Creatures</hi> or <hi>New men</hi> now but by faith, not actuall till the Refur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, we are to live as if we were raiſed againe, for the condition of the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is not to us, as the Condition of <hi>Innocency</hi> was to <hi>Adam,</hi> a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in this preſent State of this preſent State, as his was to him, to wit, the Condition of immortallty in immortallity; but ours a condition in preſent mortallity of future immortallity: ſo is it, that <hi>mortallity being ſwallowed up of life,</hi> we are preſently under the end of its Condition, <hi>Salvation,</hi> or <hi>Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</hi> Therefore as the Reſurrection cannot poſſibly be but by Chriſt, ſo the penalty cannot poſſibly be by other; it is out of the Sphear of this world, therefore one of the power of the Princes of this world, as they cannot be <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatours of the New Teſtament,</hi> ſo they cannot be <hi>puniſhers</hi> therein; Therefore to puniſh the Offenders therein, is to attempt the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and aſurpe (as much as in them lieth) his <hi>Mediatourſhip:</hi> Therefore hath he referred the contemners of his Goſpell untill the <hi>Judgment</hi> of the <hi>Laſt Day.</hi> And for that in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 49. 23. <hi>And Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and Queens the nurſing Mothers:</hi> it is a Propheſie of the deliverance of the <hi>Jewes</hi> from their <hi>Captivity,</hi> to whom <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> ſhall be aſſiſtance in their returne to the <hi>Land</hi> of their <hi>Forefathers,</hi> as <hi>ver.</hi> 19. 22. 23. 26. &amp;c. witneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Politicke Power.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Foreman, <hi>Salus populi,</hi> the ſafety of the people, is the <hi>Soveraigne Law,</hi> or fundamentall conſtitution of Civill Government; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though Majeſtracy hath been corrupted and abuſed, (as appeareth by our <hi>Evidence)</hi> to the terrour of the moſt virteous, conſcientious, well minded men, and the maintenance and protection of the wicked; ſo that it hath been perverted from the geneall good if all <hi>ſorts, ſects, and ſocieties</hi> of people, unto this or that <hi>ſort</hi> or <hi>ſect;</hi> yet this evill in Majeſtracy is to be cut off, <hi>ne pars ſincera trabatur.</hi> And Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> it appears by our <hi>Evidence,</hi> that PERSECUTION is the originall of the diſeaſe, therefore to be cut off, leaſt the whole <hi>politiqus body</hi> periſh: For where <hi>Perſecution</hi> is, what <hi>diſſenuions, mutintes, tumults, inſurrections, aproares,</hi> and <hi>diviſions;</hi> what what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121057:17"/>
                     <hi>Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Rebellions;</hi> what <hi>bloodſhed, cruelty, and inhumanity</hi> hath been by our <hi>Evidence</hi> declared, the which by our owne experience we find ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refied in divers <hi>Kingdomes, States,</hi> and <hi>Provinces:</hi> for doe we not ſee, betwixt the <hi>Catholicke Cauſe</hi> and the <hi>True Proteſtant Religion</hi> (ſo cal'd) the <hi>Chriſtian world is embrewed with blood,</hi> deſtroying and devouring one an other: the daſhing of thoſe two imperious, ambitious, inſolent Religions, the <hi>Papall</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> together beſides what it hath done to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Auſtrea,</hi> &amp;c. hath ſplit the <hi>Dominons</hi> of this <hi>politique body</hi> aſunder, that they wallow in one an others vitall blood, <hi>burning, deſtroying,</hi> and <hi>ruinating</hi> all before them; how many <hi>Townes, Villages,</hi> and <hi>ſumptenus buildings</hi> have been burne? what <hi>Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage</hi> and <hi>Meddowes</hi> laid waſt, and how many <hi>thouſands of innocent ſoules</hi> have been <hi>ſlayen</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> contrary to the end and foundation of <hi>poltique Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi> and doth not <hi>England</hi> taſt <hi>even the dregges of this Cup, yea ſwallow it downe with greedynes, that we are even drunke with one an others blood, enraged with madneſſe, crueltics,</hi> &amp;c. without all hopes of peace till one of theſe <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting Religions</hi> have devoured the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>State-Policie.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> though from <hi>Rome,</hi> the ſpirit of <hi>Perſocuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is conveyed into moſt ſects of <hi>Religion,</hi> and is dayly found to the ſhame of <hi>Religion</hi> among ſuch as are or would be counted <hi>religious,</hi> and moſt <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> being rent with ſuch <hi>perſecuting Religions,</hi> therefore the <hi>Kingdoms of Chriſtendome</hi> have judged the Toleration of divers <hi>Sects</hi> inconſiſtent with <hi>State policy;</hi> yet <hi>Politians</hi> would they conſider, need not in curing one miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheife run upon a greater; for ſuch good and wholeſome meanes might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, as in a ſmall time this <hi>violent ſpirit</hi> might be worne out, the next <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> be of a better temper, and at length <hi>Perſecution</hi> to be as rare as now common, and a more placable peaceable ſpirit conſiliated among the generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of men: And ſeeing this impatient, violent, ambitious ſpirit is ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to Civill Societies their friendſhip &amp; unity, ſo deſtructive to publike peace and ſafety: It is therefore neceſſary, that Kings and all Governours, whoſe Office is; <hi>that all may lead a peaceable and quite life under them,</hi> ſhould in policy to the generall good, ſee to the ſecuring of their <hi>Dominions</hi> from this factious ſpirit, by ſuch wholeſome ſtrict Lawes as may beſt conduce to the ſuppreſſion thereof, as of <hi>Treaſon, Rebellion,</hi> or the like; for allare <hi>Traytours and Rebels</hi> in their hearts to the publike peace, and generall good of humaine ſocieties, <hi>ſalus populi, the peoples ſafety,</hi> (which our State counteth the <hi>ſuprame Law)</hi> which are of a perſeuting ſpirit; for it is in direct oppoſition to that Law; And who more guilty then the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> when one is too mighty for the other, the <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſtronger then the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> ſtronger then the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the ſtronger is ſo ambitious and fiery zealous for his owne cauſe, eſpecially the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> that one place is too hot for them both, and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> as he is a perſecutour of the <hi>Papiſt,</hi> ſo as well as the Papiſt, is he a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121057:17"/>
Perſecutour of <hi>Anbaptiſts, Browniſts, Antinomians, Independants,</hi> &amp;c. but they perſecute none, but ſeeke the generall good, peace, and ſafety of all <hi>Sorts, Sects,</hi> and <hi>Societies</hi> of people, yea even of their Enemies; ſo that as Papiſts are Enemies and Traytours to the ſafety of all <hi>Sorts, Sects,</hi> and <hi>Societies,</hi> ſo are the Proteſtants, conſidered in this perſecuting ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, both perſecuting; therefore in this ſenſe their <hi>Religions</hi> are both <hi>trayterous, deſperate,</hi> and <hi>dangerous</hi> to the <hi>Publicke Good:</hi> Therefore it ought to be the care of thoſe Kingdomes and States where thoſe perſecuting Religions are, to purge thoſe Religions of this <hi>Malignant perſecuting ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> this <hi>trayterous diſpoſition,</hi> for Relegions may be abſolute, yea the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant more truley Proteſtant, if cured of this <hi>Peſtilentiall diſeaſe of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for indeed <hi>perſecution is no part of Religion,</hi> but a meer ſpirit of <hi>Treaſon</hi> inſenſibly inſinuated, and diſtill'd into Religions by <hi>Popes, Biſhops and Preiſts;</hi> ſo that ignorantly the members of thoſe Religions are made <hi>Traytours</hi> to their <hi>owne Rights and Liberties,</hi> and ſo enſlaved to the <hi>trayterous deſignes of the Clergie,</hi> the very roote of Treaſon; for indeed the Teachers of <hi>Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> are the <hi>Archeſt Jeſuiticall Traytours of all,</hi> whether <hi>Papiſt, Proteſtant</hi> &amp;c. ſuch as Mr. <hi>Edwards,</hi> who moſt impudently and trayterouſly ſaith in his <hi>Antipologie, that the Parliament is bound in duty, to compell all men to the Decrees of the Aſſembly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. Polit-Power.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>State-Policy, I commend your policy herein, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</hi> Mr. Edwards <hi>in ſo ſaying, is a Traytour to politique power: But I pray you proceed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. State-Policie.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Well then, as all are borne ſubjects to their Kings, ſo are Kings to ſee, that all may have their Birthright, Liberty, and Priviledge of Subjects, that all may be kept in the</hi> generall Bond of peace, <hi>of what ſort or ſect ſoever, for as</hi> Lucius Lavinius <hi>ſaid to King</hi> James, all the different members being wrapt up in the skine of one conſtitution, need no ſtronger obligement, to uphold the whole then their owne intereſt: <hi>Therefore, were the devouring principle of perſecution weeded out from betwixt all Religions, they might all enjoy their publike ſafety to the generall enlargement and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of politike power, for the ſtrength of the King lies in the multitude of people, ſo that it is moſt conſonant to State policy to include all, rather then deprive any of publike protection.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>M. <hi>Nationall-Loyalty.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mr. Foreman,</hi> this is <hi>a matter of great weight,</hi> that we have in hand, therefore <hi>not ſleightly, but ſeriouſly to be weighed, and delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately examined</hi> both from our owne knowledge and experience, as from the juſt Evidence given in by the Witneſſes, (for I conceive, this pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner is antiently knowne to us all) that wee may be better enabled
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121057:18"/>
to give in our <hi>verdict,</hi> wherefore having ſomething to ſay of antient experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I ſhall firſt deſire Mr. <hi>State-Policie,</hi> ſince he hath given us an hint of wholeſome meanes that might be uſed, to prevent and ſuppreſſe this turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent rebellious Spirit of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> that he would declare what further he hath in his thoughts thereon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>State-Polic.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>That which in it ſelfe is wicked, neither honourable to God, allowed by him, nor profitable to man, but dangerous and deſtructive to common ſafety and peace, falleth under the <hi>Sword</hi> of the Majeſtracy, and the Majeſtrate may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> uſe ſuch meanes as ſhall beſt ſecute the publike peace from the evill their of: Now ſince the generality of the people are poſſeſſed with this <hi>Evill Spirit,</hi> infuſed, nouriſhed, and preſerved in their hearts by <hi>Popes, Biſhops, Preiſts,</hi> and (at preſent in the Land) by the <hi>trayterous Synod,</hi> called the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> who labour with might and maine to eſtabliſh and ſede this trayterous <hi>ſpirit</hi> in the Land; and further, ſince all by compul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion are to be forced to the Civill peace and publike vnity, and all are to be deſended and preſerved under the publike freedome, one as well as an other; therefore to this end the Majeſtrate ought to bind all Religions, that no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion have power over other, that all in the Generall have Toleration, and none in particular be offenſive; for the <hi>Papiſt</hi> may be a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> the <hi>Proteſtant a Proteſtant</hi> without the power of Compulſion, the deprivation thereof is no wayes injurious to their Religion; as a man that hath a wen, or a bunch that growes upon any member, may be a perfect man, and that a perfect member without it: Therefore to this end a Nationall Covenant would not be inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, to engage all in this publike freedome, that as all ſhould be ſharers in it, ſo all ſhould be deſenders of it. That no <hi>Proteſtant Miniſter</hi> or other ſhould teach privately or publikely, either by <hi>preaching, writing,</hi> or <hi>conference</hi> any thing contradictory or diſtructive thereto. That no man upbraid, reproach, ſcoffe, deride, threaten, or doe any violence to any for his Religion, <hi>and ſuch like:</hi> And that this be continued from <hi>Generation</hi> to <hi>Generation</hi> under ſuch and ſuch penalties as the State ſhall thinke fit; ſo that in a ſmall time, if the Governours would hearken to the feare of the Lord, this oppreſſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is now made <hi>State Policie</hi> (condemned by the God of mercy and all mercifull men) would waxe out of date, and be caſt out as abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to God, and deſtructive to mankind: Then their feares and jealouſies one of an other, which puts them in a continuall poſture of war both offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>five and defenſive would be at an end; their Controverſies would be of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kind, falſe and equall Diſputes, and it is better and farre cheaper to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide words for Argumentation, then inſtruments of war for blowes and bloodſhed and would conduce I am ſure more to the common good and ſate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty the one doth encreaſe knowledge the other nothing but rage and revenge: by reaſoning thoſe that are ignorant would ſhortly ſee, how they and their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121057:18"/>
                     <hi>Forefathers</hi> have been cheated of the <hi>Tenth</hi> of their encreaſe, fool'd, and nurſ'd up in blinneſſe by <hi>Biſhops, Preiſts,</hi> &amp;c. meerly to uphold their greatnoſſe, ſtuffe and cram their ungodly guts, that it is become a Proverbe, <hi>as fat as a Biſhop,</hi> and how ſoone, if PERSECUTION be acquited, it may be verified on the the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> I leave that to the iſſue, only I wiſh the people to try things themſelves, and not truſt too much to their <hi>L'ppes,</hi> for their <hi>Lippes</hi> are <hi>Cozen Germaine</hi> to their <hi>Teeth,</hi> and this is moſt certain, they all <hi>ſpeake through the Teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Nation. Loyal.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> according to the <hi>Evidence</hi> we have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and reſult of our conſultation hitherto, he is guilty <hi>ipſo facto</hi> of what is laid to his charge; and for mine owne part, I know that <hi>Toleration</hi> is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Nationall Loyalty,</hi> but may well ſtand with <hi>Nationall peace,</hi> as by divers antient and moderne Examples I can make it appeare, <hi>Abraham</hi> lived among the <hi>Cannanites</hi> and <hi>Perizzites, Gen.</hi> 13. 7. &amp; 16. 3. againe he ſojourned in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Gen.</hi> 12. 10. after in <hi>Gerar,</hi> where King <hi>Abimelech</hi> bid him dwell where it pleaſed him, <hi>cap.</hi> 20. &amp; 21. 23. 24. afterwards among the <hi>Hittites, cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Lot</hi> lived in <hi>Sodom, Iſeack</hi> alſo dwelt in <hi>Gerar,</hi> yet contrary to the King and his Subjects <hi>cap.</hi> 20 <hi>Jacob</hi> lived 20. yeares with his Vncle <hi>Laban</hi> in one houſe, yet different in Religion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 30. 33. the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> lived 430. yeares in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 12. 40. afterwards were caried away to <hi>Babylon,</hi> where they remained 70. yeares, all which times they differed in Religion, yet no danger to the State: <hi>Sampſon</hi> lived among the <hi>Philiſtimes, Lot</hi> in the Land of <hi>Vz,</hi> yet their Religion though different was not diſturbant to the State: And in the time of Chriſt, when <hi>Iſraell</hi> was captive to the <hi>Romans,</hi> lived divers <hi>Sects</hi> of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions, <hi>Herodians, Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſes, Sadduces</hi> and <hi>Libertines</hi> ſuch as denyed the Reſurrection, and <hi>Samaritanes</hi> the common Religion of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> Religion, all which deffered from the common Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the State; which in all probability was the <hi>worſhip of Dima, whome all the world almoſt then worſhipped, Act.</hi> 19. 20. yet all theſe lived under the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> not any wayes injurious to his Crowne and Dignity, or diſturbant to the peace of his Government: but when <hi>Perſecution</hi> aroſe, then the State was troubled by <hi>tumults, uproares,</hi> &amp;c. And how doth <hi>Toleration</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure the State of <hi>Holland, Poland, Traſilvmia,</hi> &amp;c. their <hi>Weales, States,</hi> and <hi>Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> are well and peaceably governed, divers Religions are in their Provinces, yet all have one harmony in matters of State, all united and engaged in the generall ſafety, peace, and tranqillity of their ſeverall Kingdoms, States, and Provinces, wherein they ſo freely enjoy their ſoverall ſafeties, protection and freedomes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Liberty-of-Subject.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman</hi> beſides what I have received form the Witneſſes, of my own experience I know, that if PERSECVTION be not executed, the <hi>Liberty of the Subject</hi> (now in controverſie) cannot be ſetled in this Land; for the <hi>Anbaptiſts, Browniſts, Independants,</hi> &amp;c. true and faithfull
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121057:19"/>
Subjects to the State, that ſtood to the <hi>publike cauſe,</hi> when the <hi>Preiſts</hi> &amp; ſuch like <hi>ſcurrel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s vermine,</hi> durſt ſcarce be ſeen in it, but <hi>Jeſuitically</hi> caried themſelves in an equall ballance betwixt both, that though the King had conquered, yet moſt of them would have kept their <hi>Benefices, a wiſe generation!</hi> I ſay, theſe more <hi>noble ſpirited men,</hi> that freely ſpend their lives, fortunes, and eſtates for the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the Subject,</hi> and that from the moſt noble and rationall princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ple, <hi>the Common Good</hi> and not for <hi>ſelfe reſpect,</hi> neither thoſe of them which ſuruive, nor the ſucceders in their faith ſhall enjoy this <hi>Liberty,</hi> their juſt <hi>Birth-right,</hi> but be wholy deprived thereof, and the purchaſe of their <hi>Blood</hi> be ceaſ'd and devour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d by thoſe <hi>Presbyterian Horſe-leeches,</hi> and confined to ſuch <hi>blood-thirſty Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tle,</hi> which is directly oppoſite to the <hi>juſt Liberty of the Subject.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mpaſ. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>m.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Foreman, <hi>I have beheld the i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nnocency of their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ty of their lives,</hi> (to wit of Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, &amp;c) <hi>their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Common-wealth, their forwardnes of aſſiſtance in purſe and perſon, kow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Meetings to be ſo innocent, ſo far from confederacy or counterplots</hi> (pag. 3.) <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d yet their perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ns ſo hated, contemned, and belyed, ſuch wounds made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their conſciences, that my heart aboundeth with greife, that their miſerie ſhould be thus paſſed by, their wounds ſo wide and deepe, and no oyle of mercy powred in: ſo that me thinkes, everie man is bound in conſcience, to ſpeake and doe what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e can in the behalfe of ſuch an harmeles people as theſe.</hi> (pap. 4.) Therefore, Mr. <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> being privy to the truth of the Evidence againſt PERSECVTION, the ſole cauſer of their wounds and miſerie, I conclude him, <hi>an enemie againſt God and all goodneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> and that he is guilty of the <hi>Indictment.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Truth-&amp;-Peace.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> much I could ſay againſt the Priſoner, to witneſſe the verity of the <hi>Indictment,</hi> but for brevity ſake I ſhall referre you to the diſcovery I have made of his <hi>Impiety, Treaſon, Blood-ſhed,</hi> &amp;c. in that Booke intituled, <hi>The Bloody Tenent,</hi> and I commend unto you, and to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary peruſall of the <hi>COMMONNS</hi> and <hi>nobles</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that moſt famous peece, called, <hi>The Compaſſionate Samaritane,</hi> as a moſt exact modell of ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Light-of-Nature.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Foreman,</hi> whereas Sir <hi>Symon</hi> in the defence of PERSECVTION ſaith, that LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE <hi>opens a gate to all manner of prophaneſſe, looſeneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> might teach him, that Toleration is no Approbation, or rhe ſuffering of Religions a warrant to be of no Religion, much leſſe to publike prophaneſſe; for this comes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the nompaſſe of that which Nature teaches the moſt ignorant, therefore within the reach of publike reſtrain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, according to the Lawes of common mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y and civility, which Nature hath written in the hearts of all men natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Such publike Tranſgreſſions that are uncivill, unnaturall, and unbecome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing humaine ſociety, is <hi>open prophaneſſe</hi> and <hi>lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſeneſſe</hi> fall under the reſtraint, and correction of the Mageſtrate, whoſe power is over the things of Nature, thoſe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121057:19"/>
being offences of that kind: As the Majeſtrate is to maintaine the publicke peace, and all civill ſocieties therein, ſo is it preſerve publike modeſty, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and civillity, that there may be a generall comely demeanour as rationall creatures, ſo their carriage and publicke demeouours are to be rationall regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and comely, and not openly licentious, prophane, and blaſphenious, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to common ſenſe, reaſon, and humanity.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mr. <hi>Creation.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, we have ſpent much time, and our <hi>Uerdict</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and the caſe is ſo evident and plaine, that I thinke what is done may ſuffice, if you Mr. <hi>Orphan,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Day-of-Judgement</hi> be agreed with us in your <hi>Verdict,</hi> let us give it in: what ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                  <p>We are agreed; <hi>guilty, guilty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A</hi> Verdict: <hi>Make way there for the Juri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, hold up thy hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Maſters of the Jurie, looke upon the Priſoner, is he guilty of this <hi>Treaſon, Rebellion, Bloodſhed,</hi> &amp;c. in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and forme as he ſtands <hi>indicted,</hi> or not guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Foreman.</speaker>
                  <p>GUILTY <hi>my Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, thou haſt heard the hainous Accuſation; that hath been proved againſt thee, and the <hi>verdict</hi> the <hi>Jurie</hi> have given in up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, what canſt thou ſay for thy ſelfe, to <hi>award</hi> the ſencence of death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> paſſing againſt thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord,</hi> the Jurie have not dealt honeſtly in their <hi>verdict,</hi> wherefore I appeale from them to the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> for a tryall of their honeſty in this <hi>verdict.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, indeed thouſtand'ſt need of a <hi>Long Clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>k to cover thy kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>verie;</hi> but there is no <hi>appeale</hi> from this Court, they are no <hi>Sanctuary of refuge</hi> in this caſe, neither can I conceive ſuch worthy Gentlemen ſhould perjure themſelves, yet if thou haſt any thing elſe to ſay, to award the <hi>Sentence of death,</hi> ſpeake for thy ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I thanke your Honour, the Lord bleſſe your Honour: My Lord, I am ſo terrified in my ſelfe at the apprehenſion of death that I am not in caſe to ſpeake for my ſelfe: I beſeech your Lordſhip, that Sir <hi>Symon</hi> may ſpeake in my behalfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Sym.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord, The enemies of our peace in this matter have dealt very ſubtilly, and moſt traytorouſly againſt the</hi> reverend Aſſembly of the faithfull, <hi>the</hi> Clergie, <hi>to divide them from your Lordſhips protection, to deſtroy and hinder the worke of Reformation, &amp;c. for</hi> my Lord, <hi>this man here indicted by the name of</hi> PERSECUTION, <hi>is none of the man; for here is Mr.</hi> Nationall Conformity, <hi>Mr.</hi> Pontificall Revenue, <hi>Mr.</hi> Eccleſiaſticall Supremacy, <hi>Perſonages of Honour, and eminencie through out whole Christendome, to teſtifie with me, that this Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner hath ever endeavoured to purge the Church of God, from Hereſie, Soiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>, and all manner of irregular exorbitant courſes, and laboured for the peace of the Church,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121057:20"/>
that we may lead,</hi> a lazie and an eaſie life without God, and the people in the feare of the Clergie. <hi>Indeed my Lord, he was once of the</hi> Church of Rome, <hi>and thereupon generally branded by the name of</hi> PERSECUTION; <hi>but my Lord, for this hundred yeares and upward he hath been of the</hi> true Proteſtant Religion, <hi>even from the time of</hi> Luthar, <hi>and at this preſent</hi> en-<hi>devoureth with us the the good of the</hi> Church <hi>in its reſtitution to</hi> Prelaticall Presbytrie: <hi>And upon his</hi> ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>from</hi> Rome <hi>with</hi> Luthar, <hi>he utterly reno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nced the</hi> nicke-name <hi>of</hi> PERSE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUTION, <hi>and though unhappily through</hi> Jeſuiticall ſuggeſtions <hi>and</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s <hi>he was too frequent in the</hi> Spaniſh Inq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uiſition, <hi>and of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e by</hi> Epiſcopall ſophiſtications <hi>intiſed to offi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iate</hi> in the High Commiſſion; <hi>yet my Lord, he was ever in himſelfe an</hi> honeſt Reformer, <hi>and indeed his true name is</hi> Preſent Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>he was borne not long after the</hi> Primative times, <hi>but</hi> his nature <hi>and</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations by evil Inſtruments have been ſo much abuſd, that he had even loſt his name, <hi>and being</hi> nicke-named <hi>when he was yongue, and through long continuance of</hi> time, <hi>forgot his name, that indeed he anſwered a long time to the name of</hi> PERSECUTION, <hi>but</hi> his true <hi>and</hi> proper name <hi>is</hi> Preſent Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>which by Interpretation, is,</hi> Presbyterian Government: <hi>Wherefore my Lord, I beſeech you,</hi> conſider the ſubtilty of this malignant hereticall facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who have procured the apprehenſion and indictment of this <hi>Preſent Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> under the odious name of PERSECUTION, thereby at once to make your Honor both ruine your ſelfe, and the Presbytrie of the Kingdom: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my Lord, whether the Jurie have dealt honeſtly in their Verdict, your Honour by this may eſily diſcerne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, what ſayeſt thou to this? Is thy name <hi>Preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Reformation?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes <hi>my Lord,</hi> and my name is according to my naturall diſpoſition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>Who gave you that name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, his God-fathers and God-mothers in his Baptiſme, wherein he was made a member of the Aſſembly, and an Inheritor of the Kingdome of <hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>His God-fathers, and God-mothers? who are your God-fathers, and your God-mothers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, Mr. <hi>Eccleſiaſticall-Supremacy,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Scot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>-Government</hi> are any God-fathers, Mrs. <hi>State-Ambition,</hi> and Mrs. <hi>Church-Revennue</hi> are my God-mothers, and I was ſprinkled into the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines</hi> at the take<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the late <hi>ſolemne League and Covenant.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, he is at this time <hi>Primate</hi> and <hi>Metr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>pol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> over all the <hi>Eccleſiaſt. Courts</hi> of Tyranny in the world, the <hi>Spaniſh Inquiſition,</hi> the <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> and now our Divince have <hi>ſprinkled</hi> his <hi>federall Holyneſſe</hi> into their Aſſembly, and hereupon chang'd his name from PERSECUTION, and <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> him <hi>Preſent Reformation.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121057:20"/>
Judg</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis ſtrange, that at the makeing of the late ſolemne League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant boodthirſty PERSECUTION ſhould be Anabaptized Preſent Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; then here's a Deſigne of blood in the Covenant, if under the name of Reformation the Clergie have infuſed the trayterous bloodthirſty ſpirit of Perſecution into it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Human.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Lord, there was never any Nationall or Provinciall Synod, but ſtrengthned the hands of PERSECUTION, and that under the vizor of Religion:</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>And my Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn's</hi> agitation for PERSECU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION, is on purpoſe, to ſave this <hi>villaine,</hi> to cut their throats, that hazard, and ſpend their lives and fortunes for Vs, and for the State of the Kingdome, ſuch as have <hi>been faithfull in the publike Service, never tainted with Treaſon, or double dealing,</hi> though the <hi>Kings negotiation</hi> with large promiſes have attemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it, even ſuch cheifly, as they brand with the names of <hi>Anaaptiſts, Browniſts,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe notwithſtanding, they would have depriv'd of the <hi>liberty of the ſubject,</hi> yea of <hi>the liberty of their lives;</hi> and the ſole cauſe hereof is, <hi>becauſe they labour to informe your</hi> L. <hi>with rationall principles, and are zealous inquirers into the Goſpel, from thence diſcovering the iniquity of the pontificall Clergie, and (labouring for the</hi> common good) <hi>communicate their underſtandings to the benefit of others,</hi> which proveing prejuditiall to the <hi>wicked ends of the Clergy,</hi> they labour with oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brions names, lyes &amp; ſlanders to make ſuch odious, the better accompliſh their ends, and in this <hi>Deſigne</hi> they <hi>have plaid their parts,</hi> for ſhould PERSECU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION be <hi>put to death,</hi> the <hi>whole Clergy</hi> feare to be <hi>undone,</hi> as their <hi>exceptions</hi> againſt LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE did manifeſt; they are afraid of the <hi>mercy of the people,</hi> they cannot endure <hi>to ſerve only for Conſcience,</hi> their <hi>tongues are even with their bellyes, pin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ts, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>oyle the Preiſts, ſhut your hand; and there's a generall ſilence,</hi> you may be <hi>Anabaptiſt, Browniſt,</hi> or what you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, if the matter be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rought to that paſſe: This is that they feare my Lord, Therefore, would they have their hands ſtrengthned with <hi>PERSECUTION,</hi> to prevent it, let who will periſh, if they ſtand. Moreover, my Lord, thoſe very men which plead for PERSECUTION, are the ſame, even this man, Sir <hi>Iohn,</hi> is the very man, that in the dayes of the Biſhops complained; and conteſted againſt PERSECUTION, uſed all poſſible meanes to be delivered out of his <hi>Epiſeopall Pawes,</hi> endevoured to caſt him out of the <hi>High Commiſſion;</hi> but as ſoone as thoſe <hi>underling Divines</hi> are from under their <hi>Epiſcopall Task-maſters,</hi> and beginning to encroach upon your Lordſhips power, preſently take this notorious bloody Traitour, PERSECUTION, ſtript by your Lordſhip of his <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> habit, and out of their zeale dreſſe him in a divine <hi>Synedicall garbe,</hi> and chang his name from PERSECUTION, and <hi>criſten</hi> him <hi>Reformation;</hi> ſo to engage your Lordſhip, and the Kingdomes of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> in blood, to ſettle and eſtabliſh bloody <hi>Perſecution</hi> by <hi>Covenant</hi> over the <hi>Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iences</hi> of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121057:21"/>
honeſt and faithfull men unto the State, under the ſpecious and godly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of <hi>Reformation,</hi> as Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> one of their Champions manifeſts, who is ſo impudent, as to aſſert, <hi>that your Lordſhip is bound to compell all men to the Decrees of the Synod,</hi> (aſcribing to them, as the Papiſts to the Pope,) <hi>an infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible unerring ſpirit,</hi> and openly proclaimes, that Toleration of ſuch honeſt faithfull Subjects, as <hi>Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Independants, Antinomians,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>to be in direct oppoſition to the Covenant, and though before they might have beene law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully tole are yet now they cannot under breach of the Covenant:</hi> Conſider <hi>My Lord,</hi> is not this Jeſuiticall ſubtilty, moſt deſperate and ſecret deluſion, that by this Covenant they would engage your Lordſhip, either to be a Covenant break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or elſe intringe the Liberty of the Subject entruſted by the <hi>Common people</hi> in your hands, one of theſe is inavoydable, and yet all under the coulour of <hi>Reformation, the true Proteſtant Religion, the cauſe of God,</hi> and I know not what; <hi>in nomine Domini perpetrant onine malum;</hi> ſo that it is moſt certaine, that this fellow, whoſe name Sir <hi>Symon</hi> feigneth to be <hi>Reformation,</hi> is abſolute <hi>PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SECUTION,</hi> ſo that had theſe Reformers but as much power as <hi>Queen Maryes</hi> Clergie, their Reformation would conclude in fire and faggot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>oh inſufferable Aſſembly! I ſee 'tis dangerous for a State to pin their faith upon the ſleive of the Clergie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Further <hi>my Lord,</hi> whereas others are impoveriſhed, ſpend their eſtates, engage and looſe their lives in this Quarrell, they are enriched, and advanced by it, ſave their purſes and perſons, cram and fill their greedy guts too filthy to be caried to a <hi>Beare,</hi> heape up wealth to themſelues, and give not a penny, while others (againſt whom they exclaime) venture and expend all, yea my Lord, this great go belly'd Idoll, called the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines,</hi> is not aſhamed in this time of State neceſſity, to guzle up and devoure dayly more at an ordinary meale, then would make a Feaſt for <hi>Bell and the Dragon,</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all their <hi>fat Benefices,</hi> forſooth they muſt have their foure ſhillings a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ceco by the day, for litting in conſtollidation; and poore men when they had fil'd all <hi>Benefices</hi> with good Trencher men of their owne Presbyterean Tribe, they move your Lordſhip, that all Miniſters may be wholy freed from all manner of Taxations, that now the Trade of a Presbyter is the beſt Trade in <hi>England,</hi> all are taxed, and it goes free; poore men that have not bread to ſtill the cry of their children, muſt either pay or goe in perſon to the wars, while thoſe devouring Church-lubbers live at caſe, feed on dainties neither pay nor goe themſelves but preach out our very hearts, they make it a caſe of conſcience to give all, but wiſe men the'l give hope: let the ſicke, the lame and maimed Souldiers, and thoſe that that have loſt their limbs, and begin the ſtreets, let women that have loſt their husbands, let parents that have loſt their children, let children that have loſt their parents, and let all that have or ſuffer oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and miſery, in and for the publike cauſe conſider this, and be no longer
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121057:21"/>
riden and jayded by Clergy Maſters; but to give the Divell his due, one thing to their commendations I have obſerved, that they are ſo zealouſſy affected with the honour of their cloth, that 'twere pitty to diiroable them of their Caſloke garbe to be led in a ſtring from Weſtminiſter to Allgate in Leatherne Jackets, and Mattokes on their ſhoulders; and my Lord, though ſome thinke they would do the State more good in Leatheren Jackets &amp; Mattokes then in long Cloakes and Caſſockes, yet me thinks, they would doe the State better ſervice with their Canonical Girdles, were the knot ty'd in the right place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Simon,</hi> we convocated the Aſſembly to conſult with about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, not arrogating to our ſelves, or aſcribing to them a Spirit of infallability, conſidering that we are but Parliament men, not Gods, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we made tryall of their advice, but for them hereupon to arogate Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy over the State and people, lay claime to an unerring ſpirit and perſwade us, <hi>(as Edwards in his Autipol. ſaith)</hi> that we take it for granted, that the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions of their Debates, Controverſies, and Conſulations are according to the mind <hi>of</hi> Chriſt, becauſe We cal'd them together, and hereupon to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell all men to their Decrees, is moſt impudent preſumption, and popiſh arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance; We did not ſuppreſſe the <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> to ſubject Our Selves to an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> race out <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> to ſet up <hi>Presbyterian Prelacy,</hi> for what more <hi>Prelaticall,</hi> what more <hi>exorbitant</hi> then ſuch preſumption, tis a meere <hi>Monopole of the Spirit</hi> Sir <hi>Symon:</hi> you have ſo plaid the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> as it ſeemes, We have only put downe the <hi>men,</hi> not the <hi>Function;</hi> caught the ſhaddow, and let goe the ſubſtance: while We were ſupproſſing <hi>Primates, Metrapolitanes, Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Eccleſiaſicall Courts, Canons, Injunctions, Decrees,</hi> &amp;c. you have ſo ſubtilly carried the buſineſſe, as it ſeemes, <hi>Primacy, Metrapolitaniſme, Prcla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> &amp;c. ſhrunke into the <hi>Presbytry,</hi> and our <hi>High Commiſſion</hi> turn'd into an <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly of Divines;</hi> We out of Our good intentions <hi>caſt out this Evill Spirit</hi> thence, and it entered it ſeemes, into theſe <hi>Swine,</hi> who thus headlong run up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own deſtruction, <hi>(the Divellbath brough his hogges to a faire Market)</hi> arrogating an <hi>infallability,</hi> and a <hi>ſupremacy</hi> over Us, and the people, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning PERSECUTION, when they were perſecuted, but commending and approving it, if they may peſecute: Truly Sir <hi>Synton,</hi> you have out run the Conſtable, your ambition is a little too ſwift for your policie: What breath out threatnings, menaces, and perſecutions openly, before you have power to perſecuted ſure you were not in your wits; when they were vented.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Human.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, they have <hi>ſet</hi> even till they'r run mad, you might do well to adjorne them to <hi>Bedlam;</hi> for my Lord, they are raging mad; to have the innocent blood of the Anabaptiſts, Browni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s, Independants, &amp;c.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, they have over ſtuddied themſelves, and crack'd their wits in finding out a Religion for us; poore men they have been mightily puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about it, it hath coſt them the conſumption of many fat <hi>Pigge, Chicken,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121057:22"/>
capon,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>infuſion</hi> of many <hi>a cup of ſacke,</hi> to bring it to birth, and after ſuch <hi>dalerous pangs,</hi> and <hi>bitter throwes</hi> for almoſt theſe two yeares, who would have though, they ſhould be delivered of ſuch a <hi>ridiculous vermine,</hi> called, a <hi>Presbyter; parturiunt montes, naſcitur ridiculus mus:</hi> And now my Lord, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this <hi>mountanous delivery,</hi> they are at their wits end, what dreſſing to put it out in, all the Taylours in the Kingdome are not able to content them, what to doe they know not, and now the matters worſe then ever it was, they had thought to have ſhewne the world it in the godly ſhape of <hi>Reformation,</hi> but upon examination, 'tis found to be <hi>PERSECUTION,</hi> a ſad event! there is no way now, but <hi>Bedlam</hi> for our Doctours, it may chance to chaſtize them into their wits againe, and then upon their ſecond thoughts, it may be, they'l be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke themſelves, to put a <hi>Blew Bonnet</hi> upon't, and then 'twill paſſe from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to <hi>Scotland,</hi> and from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England</hi> againe without Queſtion or controule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Indge.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> Webleſſe God, that hath put it into the hearts of thoſe honeſt godly people, (though publikely deſpiſed and hated) thoſe faithfull friends and lovers of the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> whome you <hi>nicke-name Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, Independants,</hi> &amp;c. to diſcover and detect unto us the <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiticall</hi> and <hi>Trayterous Deſignes</hi> of the <hi>Synod</hi> with the hazard of their Liberties and for ought they know of their lives and fortunes; for ſhould they not ventured themſelves in the diſcovery of ſuch a ſubtile generation, We ſhould have been kept ignorant through their zealous pretences and had there been a mountaine more of their villany, it ſeemes they would have covered it with a <hi>vaile of teares, Faſtings, affected prayers,</hi> and the like, from Our diſcerning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is an approved truth, that ſuch as are called</hi> Anabaptiſts, Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts &amp;c. <hi>have in all Ages ventured, yea given up their lives, to enforme Kings, Kingdomes, Parliaments,</hi> and <hi>States</hi> in things that concerne their peace, and the glory of God, <hi>which ubough condemned at firſt, afterwards have proved no other; yea ſuch as your Lordſhips Predeceſſours have condemned by peuall Lawes, Statutes, &amp;c. which now your Lordſhip through the mercy of God find otherwiſe, and it is we that reape the benefit of their blood in the ſuppreſſion of Epiſcopall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction, High Commiſſion, &amp;c. not they; for their ſufferings, and their teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny have detected and informed us of their unlawfulneſſe, it being their cuſtome my Lord, to weare out the</hi> Myſteric of Iniquity <hi>with their blood: And now my Lord, we that have received vantage by their bitter ſufferings, ſhall we boaſt our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? it were ungrtitude to God, and inhumanity to them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iudge.</speaker>
                  <p>True: We find by dayly experience, that the <hi>Seperates</hi> are not ſuch as ground their Religion on ſelfe ends, for like <hi>Salamanders in the fire,</hi> they live in the heate of <hi>Perſecution,</hi> they ſpare not their lives, to witneſſe the innocende of their Cauſe, the fire of <hi>Perſecution</hi> cannot conſume, but endames them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards their God and the Truth; the menacing of Kings and Governours,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121057:22"/>
and cruelties of their greateſt Adverſaries hinders not their teſtimony; this we find, when euer they are convented before Vs, even to our aſtoneſhment; and we further find, it is not their owne good alone that they aime at, but the generall good of all men, that all (one as well as an other) may lead an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and a quiet life under Our Protection, and We have to our benefit) found the bleſſing of God upon their endeavours, as the hopefull and glorious ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in the Conqueſt of <hi>Yorke,</hi> which envie and malice it ſelfe cannot deny, was inſtrumentally atcheived by their valour and ſidelity: Wherefore in juſtice to their uprightneſſe, and faithfulnes to that truſt repoſed in Vs for the publike Good; the Liberty and property of the Subject, We may not deny them the benefit of Subjects, but as they are faithfull parties in the generall venture, ſo to be heriditatory to the generall purchaſe, having as juſt a Right thereto by the price of their blood as Our Selves, for that which is purchaſed by blood, all the purchaſers have an equall right to the thing purchaſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, but our <hi>Deſſembly Doctours</hi> teach otherwiſe, yet I think if your Lordſhip ſhould ſettle <hi>Anabaptiſtrie</hi> or the like, even that which they now perſecuts and threaten, preach and pray againſt, and forewarne the people off, as hereticall and damnable, provided you ſhould endow it with <hi>goodly fat Benefices,</hi> and <hi>ſanctifie</hi> it with the <hi>hallowed Ordinance for Tythes, Offerings, Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> &amp;c. queſtionleſſe the generallity of thoſe Perſecutiones of <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> would have the wit to turne <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for their Religion is moved upon the Wheele of the State; when the State was for <hi>Biſhops,</hi> then they were for <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and were very <hi>Canonicall Surpliſſe men, Altar bowers,</hi> and the like, and the preciſeſt ſort thoſe that are now our moſt zealous <hi>Presbyters)</hi> did then ſo comply &amp; conforme to <hi>Epiſcopall ſuperſtition,</hi> as they kept their <hi>Benefices,</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept here and there one of the honoſter ſort,) while the <hi>honeſt Seperate</hi> (coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nothing too deare for his God) did openly reſiſt and witneſſe againſt it, even to impriſonments, deprivation of goods, &amp;c. But our temporizing Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, our <hi>State Proteſtant Miniſters</hi> are not ſo ſimple to ſwime againſt the ſtreame, they are <hi>wiſer in their generation,</hi> for they know moſt wealth goes that way, as long as your <hi>Ordnance is laden</hi> with <hi>Tythes, Offerings</hi> and <hi>Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> they'l be ſure to <hi>give fire;</hi> but ſhould the State deprive their Religion of all <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Revenue,</hi> of <hi>Parſonages, Tythes,</hi> &amp;c. yea, ſhould it be this very <hi>Presbyterid</hi> they ſo aime at, that they ſhould ſo impoveriſh, certainly we ſhould have <hi>more Pariſhes</hi> then <hi>Presbyters,</hi> more <hi>Steeples</hi> then <hi>Doctours;</hi> then they would no be ſo hot for <hi>Presbytry,</hi> ſo zealous to perſecute its oppoſers, I would your Lordſhip would make tryall, call in but your <hi>Ordinance for Tythes,</hi> and turne them to <hi>the good will of people,</hi> and then—<hi>a tyth Pigge wil be ſold for a penny.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>Well notwithſtanding the Doctrine and ſubtilty our Divines we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deale ſo unworthely with thoſe honeſt men, but muſt by the <hi>grace of God</hi> being by them better informed, proceed to <hi>Sentence</hi> againſt this <hi>Malefacture</hi> according to the juſt <hi>Verdict</hi> of the <hi>Jurie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:121057:23"/>
               <head>PERSECUTION <hi>fals upon his knees.</hi>
               </head>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Good my Lord, have mercy upon me, I beſeech your Houour even for the <hi>Clergies ſake,</hi> have mercy upon me; conſider my Lord, that in my death is their ruine, it will be the greateſt in road upon the Divines of Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endome, that ever was made. Oh!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I beſeech you</hi> my Lord, <hi>by the Myſterie of their holy Convocation, by their agony, and bloody ſweate, by their Croſſe and Paſſion at my ſhamefull approaching death and buriall,</hi> Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By their glorious Reſurrection, and Aſcention from the Pulpit above the State: By the coming of the Holy Ghoſt to them in Cloake Bagge from Scotland,</hi> Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the late ſolemne League and Covenant: By the 400. and 50. l. for the Copy of their Directory: By all the fat Benefices, and goodly Revenues of the Clergie,</hi> Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the Apocripha writings and non-ſenſe Arguments of Mr.</hi> Edwards: <hi>By the diſtracted thoughts and ſubitaine apprehenſions of Mr.</hi> Prinne: <hi>By the Deſignes of the Clergie: By their fained teares: By their hypocriſie: By their falſe Gloſſes, Interpretations, and Sophiſtications,</hi> Good Lord deliver me.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By the Advance of the</hi> mickle Armie <hi>into the South: By the late innocent and undefiled Ordinance for Tythes: By all that is neare and deare unto the Clergie, the pompe and glorie of this world,</hi> Good Lord deliver me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, what would'ſt thou have? here's no place of mercy for thee, the Vengance of God cannot be diſpenſ'd with, thou art not in the <hi>High Commiſſion,</hi> nor before the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> this is a Court where juſtice muſt take place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my Lord, I beſeech your Lordſhip for the mercy of this honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Bench: My Lord, I am a Clergie man, and beſeech your Honour for the benefit of my Clergie: I have been of all the Vniverſities of Chriſtendom, have taken all their Degrees, proceeded through all Eccleſiaſticall Orders and Functions, and my Lord, at preſent am under the Holy Order of Presbytrie, and I hope a Presbyter ſhall find favovr in your eyes: Wherefore I beſeeth you my Lord, that I may have the benefit of Degration.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, be contented, you ſhall be ſent to the place of Degradation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Good my Lord, let not a Presbyter come to ſo ſhamefull an end, I beſeech this Honourable Bench, that I may be repreeved but as long as the Synod and Presbytrie endure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>No PERSECUTION, ſuch is thy Treaſon, Rebllion, &amp;c. as cannot be diſpenſd with.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Perſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my Lord, a pſalme of mercy, I beſoech your Honour, a pſalme of mercy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121057:23"/>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>No PERSECUTION, no; prepare to heare thy Sentence.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hereupon this enſuinge Letter was privately conveyed to</hi> Juſtice Conformity.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To the right worſhipfull <hi>Iuſtice Conformity,</hi> all bleſſing and benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from his <hi>Holyneſſe</hi> Sir <hi>SYMON,</hi> and his Son Sir <hi>IOHN.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Right worſhipfull,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teſe are to adjure you, as you will Anſwer it before</hi> VS, <hi>at the great and dreadfull</hi> DAY <hi>of</hi> OUR <hi>Claſſicall exaltation above all perſons in the Kingdome, that you forthwith ſollicite my Lord, to ſuſpend his</hi> Sentence <hi>but till the</hi> advance of the mickle Armie into the South, <hi>for then we feare not the procurement of his plena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pardon; and for your encouragement herein laſt night my Son</hi> Jacke <hi>and I went into our</hi> Presbyterian ware-houſe, <hi>and have taken a liſt of all the Inſtruments of torture and torment already prepared for our Deſigne: to wit,</hi> triple knotty cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded whips, Gagges, Pillories, Stockes, Sharpe Knifes, Pincers, hot burning Irons, Halters, Gallowes, Gybbets, Rackes, Spits, Fine-forkes, Gridirons, Axes, Sawes Fleſhhookes, firery Furnaces, hot Ovens, boyling Caldrons, Fire and Faggot cloſe Priſons, darke and noyſome Dungeons, Fetters, Manaeles, <hi>all in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,</hi> moſt bloody and cruell Executioners, terrible and Diviliſh Tormentours <hi>as,</hi> Presbyterian Hangmen, Goalers, <hi>&amp;c. beſides multitudes of</hi> Synodean Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranies <hi>newly invented, not yet diſcovered to the people, ſuch as never either by</hi> Pope, Biſhop, <hi>on their adherents were deviſed: and though we have prepared thoſe Divel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Inſtruments, yet we ſhall not be ſo indiſcreet, to ruſh them in all on a ſuddaine; no, we ſhall obſerve the temper of the people, the courſe of times, make a graduall progreſſion, now a little, and then a little, and alwayes a moſt godly and holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence to uſher in a damnable and wicked deſignes if in the payſing a buſineſſe wee find it ſo he avy, that neither</hi> Synod, Divell, <hi>nor</hi> Presbyter <hi>can lift, we'll ſuſpend the matter, and inſenſibly prepare the people for the entertainment thereof, which by our vaine-glorious faſting, hypocriticall teares, prayres, and ſuphiſticall Serimans we ſhall eaſily doe: And for your further encouragement underſtand; there are of certaine, from a late</hi> Conſiſtorie <hi>of</hi> Divels <hi>diſpatched</hi> ſeaven foule Spirits a pecce <hi>for every</hi> Presbyter <hi>throughout</hi> England, <hi>to attend them in their</hi> Parochiall Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction; <hi>ſo that a</hi> Presbyter <hi>ſhall be</hi> ſeaven times <hi>worſe then a</hi> Biſhop, <hi>for it is intended, he ſhall be</hi> more fearce and cruell then his followes, <hi>therefore</hi> Woe, Woe <hi>unto thoſe</hi> Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, <hi>&amp;c. thoſe curſed Heretickes, for thoſe</hi> preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Feinds <hi>expect but the</hi> word of commaund, <hi>to dovoure them up: But</hi> Mr William, <hi>all this will come to nothing, if this Priſoner be put to death, you ſee thoſe Sectaries have had ſuch freedome of ſpeech that my Son</hi> Jacke <hi>and I can doe no good; now, there being not ſuch a conſiderable perſon in this County as your ſelf to prevaile,</hi> WEE <hi>therefore charge you, as your hope to be a</hi> Judge, <hi>faile not at this dead lift</hi> for your Eares; <hi>indeed he's in your debt, but he vowes by your</hi> fiat juſtitia, <hi>that if you prevaile, he'll provide you a</hi> paire <hi>of</hi> better <hi>and</hi> longer, <hi>then ever you had:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121057:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121057:24"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121057:25"/>
Hereof faile not, and we ſhall not be backward to anſwer your deſerts, when,</hi> WE and the parliament, <hi>ſhall be Commenced by.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your intire Freinds, Sir SYMON SY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOD, and Sir JOHN PRESBYTER.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="testimony">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Conformity.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, were your Lordſhip but rightly informed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this Priſoner under the name of Mr. PERSECUTION, what he is, and from whence he came, your Honour would leſſe wonder at his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ations and dilatory pleaes, to award the Sentence of death, for were he guilty, what would not a man doe for his life? <hi>skin for skin, and all that a i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> will be give for his life,</hi> but ſuch is his innocency, that the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt him have been altogether upon falſe grounds; for whereas by the <hi>Evidence</hi> he is aſſerted to be born ſoon after the <hi>time of Innocency,</hi> and by them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>andeth charged with all the Innocent blood ſpilt upon the whole earth: I ſhall by your Lordſhips favour upon good grounds make it appeare, to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, for my Lord, this priſoner is not yet above an 100. yeares of age, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing borne in <hi>Geneva,</hi> of very good <hi>Lutheran</hi> and <hi>Calveniſh</hi> parentage, about the yeare 1544. where he was very well educated and inſtructed both in the Tongues and Liberall Sciences; and upon a certaine time going to Sea, he was by a great wind raiſed by <hi>Belg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>bub</hi> the Prince of Divels blowne into <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> And being ſo neare us, forth of his zeale and pious affection to reforme the Church of the <hi>Eiſcopall Prelacy</hi> to <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> he occaſioned the <hi>riſing of the Scots</hi> as <hi>one man</hi> to oppoſe that power, againſt which ever ſince he hath conteſted, and he lately advanced with their <hi>mickle Armie</hi> to the Leagure be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Yorke,</hi> and for all this, he received many an affront by <hi>Gronewels</hi> ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall <hi>Brigade,</hi> and from thence taking his joyrney through <hi>Derby, Stafford, Coventry,</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> where performing much good ſervice he came to <hi>London,</hi> ſince whoſe coming, old Grand Mr. PERSECUTION char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the Indict<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ent and convicted by the Jurie, was happily and timely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted uppon <hi>Tower Hill,</hi> by all which it appeareah, that the Witneſſes that have given in Teſtimony againſt this priſoner, the Gentleman at the Bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, have greatly abuſed him, your Lordſhip, and the Jurie, he not being the perſon charged, and conſequently innocent of the crimes laid to his charge, he being Indeed as reall an adverſary to Old Mr. <hi>PERSECUTION,</hi> as any Gentleman of this whole County; hereof if your Lordſhip make any doubt, I beſeech you; that a <hi>Farrier may</hi> be called into the Court, who may make a perfect diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to your Lordſhip of his age, by opening his mouth and vewing his Teeth, whoſe <hi>yongue, ſmall, Presbyterean Pegges</hi> have no proportion betwixt the <hi>Great Twangs,</hi> and <hi>Boariſh Tuskes</hi> of Old Mr. <hi>PERSECUTION:</hi> And beſides this my Lord, to teſtiſie what I have ſaid, to be anthenticke, there are hand reds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>mickle Armie,</hi> whoſe abſence have occaſioned this his inability to juſtifie
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121057:25"/>
and cleare himſelfe, but if your Lordſhip pleaſe but to adjcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e the buſines but till their <hi>mickle Advance</hi> into the South, the matter ſhall be made cleare unto your Honour, for then we make no queſtion to awe and cruſh thoſe He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall falſe witneſſes, and advance Presbytry to its ſuper Prelaticall Throne of <hi>CLASSICALL SUPREMACY,</hi> and though at firſt it be but <hi>jure H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> a little five and faggot will quickly Commence it <hi>jure divino.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>J. Reaſs.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I am much affraid of a Conſpiracy betwixt Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> and Sir <hi>Iohn Presbyter</hi> with Juſtice <hi>Confomity,</hi> whome like an Ignora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us they have perſwaded into their Combination, how to delude your Lordſhip, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to deliver <hi>PERSECUTION</hi> from the juſtice of this Court; You may eaſily perceave, how they would pinch your Lordſhips Noſe with a paire of <hi>Scotch-Spectacles,</hi> and fixe a paire of <hi>long Synodian Eares</hi> unto your Lordſhips head, that your Lordſhip might ſee nothing but <hi>Blew Caps,</hi> heare nothing but <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodian Thunder;</hi> but I hope your Honour is thoroughly ſenſible hereof; yet leaſt your Lordſhips Innocency, and honeſt endeavoures for the generall and equall Rights and Liberties of the Common People, ſhould be circumvented and perverted by their policie, I ſhall (hoping my plaine dealing meerly (I call God to witneſſe) out of unfeigned love unto your Honour, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Good of all the Common People ſhall not be recompenſed with your High Diſpleaſure) preſent the cunning inſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>uations and ſubtile fictions of Juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Conformity</hi> in their true ſhape; for whereas he ſaith, that this preſont Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner is not the perſon indicted, and convicted of Treaſon, Rebellion, &amp;c this being but a yong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e man, the other very old, I can aſſure your Lordſhip, that he is herein meerly deluſive, for the man is the very ſame, only through the adviſe of Sir JOHN he hath made uſe of a Presbyterian Barber, who hath ſhaven from his head, his old deformed Treſſes, cropt of his haire above the eares after the halfe moon faſhion, taught him the Presbyterian poſture of his eyes, plaiſtered up the wrinkles of his bended brow with <hi>Scotch morter,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he hath acquired a more ſmooth Synodian countenance, but in a ſmall time if he be let alone, he'l be as terrible and frightfull as ever; for his pritty ſmall Pegges that he ſpeakes off, your L. is therein miſinformed; for the <hi>Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> that rearched his mouth, was a <hi>Presbytere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Horſe Doctour,</hi> prepared on purpoſe by yongue Sir JOHN for that very end, who diſcovered to your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> only the upper part of his fore teeth, whereas were his mouth but ſearched by an <hi>Independant Farrier,</hi> he would diſcover beſides thoſe in the hinder part of his Claſſicall Jawes, his Great Iron Fangs, as great and terrible as thoſe ſpoaken of by <hi>Daniell, cap.</hi> 7. 7. And as for the good ſervice Juſtice <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity</hi> mentioned, that be performed in his Roade from <hi>Scatland</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> It was ſo good, that the Priſoners there care for no more of his goodneſſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121057:26"/>
for if he <hi>mumble</hi> us thus with his <hi>yongue ſmall Presbyterian Pegges,</hi> what bloody maſſacrie, what cruell cruſhing of bones, rending, tearing and devouring of fleſh, muſt we expect, if your Lordſhip permit him the uſe of his dreadfull devouring <hi>Tuskes,</hi> his huge monſterous <hi>iron Fangs,</hi> but I hope your Lordſhip will firſt grant him the favour of an <hi>Independant Tooth-drawer,</hi> and then wee ſhall not greatly feare his <hi>Gun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>es:</hi> And concerning the <hi>Mickle Armie,</hi> my Lord, you may perceive how they would bind your hands from the execution of juſtice by the force of Armes, as though the wiſedome of this Court were to be inſlaved to ſuch ſiniſter reſpects; my Lord, it is highly dere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atory to your Honour, and here are ſufficient <hi>Engliſh Evidence,</hi> to prove this old ſeducer, to be PERSECUTION himſelfe, as hath been manifeſt before your Honour; let not the people be thus depriv'd of juſtice, they did not in chuſing your Lordſhip to this place, wherein you are, intend the makeing of themſelves ſlaves in any the leaſt kind, to <hi>Synods, Sir Johns, force of armes,</hi> or the like, or to put themſelves at ſo vaſt a diſtance, as to make their addreſſes to you, as to ſome <hi>Dietie,</hi> but in their chuſing of you, authoriſed and entruſted you, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate and preſerve their native and juſt Liberties in generall, yea, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them with your ſelfe: therefore you cannot without betraying this Truſt, by any <hi>coerſive power</hi> ſubject any of their conſciences, perſons, or eſtates to any <hi>Ecoleſiaſticall Jurisdiction</hi> whatſoever: And now ſeeing this <hi>vile per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> at the <hi>Barre</hi> hath been legally <hi>indicted, araigned,</hi> and <hi>convicted,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by found an Arch enemio and Traytour to the peoples common Liberty and Safety, <hi>Judgement</hi> and <hi>Execution</hi> ought forthwith to paſſe upon him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly, that this <hi>Hypocritical Phariſie,</hi> this <hi>blood-thirſty Catiffe,</hi> this <hi>Long Gown'd M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>ntebanke</hi> with his ſpirituall deluſions may no longer cheate the world, as he hath done.</p>
               </sp>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hereupon the Court proceedeth to Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iudge.</speaker>
                  <p>Make Proclamation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Crier.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O—yes, every man keep ſilence &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>With much patience this Coure hath heard the ſeverall, pleaes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt PERSECUTION, and LIBERTY-OF-CONSCIENCE u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>sd on both ſides; having ſeriouſly weighed the ſame in the Ballance of equity, hath found PERSECUTION and his Abettours with all their <hi>Pleas</hi> too light, even meere ſubtile, alrie, and empty deluſions: It is therefore the Sentence of this Court concerning Sir <hi>Symon,</hi> and Sir <hi>John Presbyter,</hi> who have thus <hi>Ieſuitically</hi> endeavoured to pervert the juſtice of this <hi>Court</hi> by their falſe, their ſubtile, and <hi>Trayterous</hi> ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſtions in the behalf of this notorious bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>Malefactour</hi> PERSECUTION, that Sir <hi>SIMON</hi> be committed <hi>cloſe Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to <hi>King Henry the eigh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s Chappell,</hi> there to be kept in <hi>Parliamentory ſafe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121057:26"/>
cuſtody,</hi> till the <hi>GREAT ASSISES,</hi> held in the firſt yeare of the <hi>RAIGNE</hi> of our <hi>Soveraigne Lord CHRIST, (when the Kingdom, and the greatnes of the Kingdome under the whole Heaven ſhalbe given to the Saints of the moſt High)</hi> there, and then to be <hi>Araigned</hi> with the reſt of his <hi>Holy Tribe,</hi> whether <hi>Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, Nationall, Provinciall,</hi> or <hi>Conſiſtoriall Counſels,</hi> or <hi>Synods</hi> whatſoever, before his <hi>Highneſſe</hi> the <hi>KING OF KINGS,</hi> and <hi>LORD OF LORDS.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>I. Reaſ.</speaker>
                  <p>And my Lord, in the meane time to keep his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> in action, I beſeech, your Honour, that he may <hi>Synodicate</hi> a full Reſolution to theſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuing <hi>Queries.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether it doth not as much conduce to the <hi>Subjects Liberty</hi> ſtill to be ſubjected to <hi>Epiſcopall uſurpation,</hi> as to be given over to <hi>Presbyterian cruelty?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether it would not been more profitable for the Kingdome of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to have forthwith hired a <hi>Coach and twelve Horſes</hi> to have ſet a <hi>Directory</hi> from <hi>Scotland,</hi> then to have ſpent the <hi>learned conſultations, pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us debates,</hi> and <hi>ſacred concluſions</hi> of ſuch an <hi>holy,</hi> ſuch a <hi>reverend,</hi> ſuch an <hi>heavenly,</hi> ſuch a <hi>godly,</hi> ſuch a <hi>learned,</hi> ſuch a <hi>pious,</hi> ſuch a <hi>grave,</hi> ſuch a <hi>wiſe,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſollid,</hi> ſuch a <hi>diſcreete,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſpirituall,</hi> ſuch an <hi>evangellicall,</hi> ſuch an <hi>infallible,</hi> ſuch a <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſuper-celeſtiall Quire of Angels,</hi> ſuch a <hi>ſuperlative Aſſembly of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines</hi> for almoſt theſe two yeares ſpace, after the proſuſe and vaſt expence of above <hi>fourty thouſand pounds,</hi> beſides their <hi>goodly fat Benefices,</hi> upon their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring <hi>Guts,</hi> for an <hi>Engliſh DIRECTORY</hi> of worſhip equivolent to the <hi>Scotch DIRECTORY?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. Whether this Directory ſtanding in ſo many thouſands to fumble it to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and the Copy ſould at 400. &amp; 50. <hi>l.</hi> be not of more value then the Writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles?</p>
                  <p n="4">4 Whether St. <hi>Peters Chaire</hi> doth not becomme a <hi>Presbyter,</hi> as well as a <hi>Biſhop?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. Whether the late divine Ordinance for Tythes, Offerings, Oblations, and Conventions be not better Goſpell, and in all <hi>Presbyterian wiſedome</hi> to be preferred and provided before the <hi>Directory for the worſhip of God?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Cives, Cives, quaerenda pecunia primum,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Virtus poſt nummos.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </q>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Judge.</speaker>
                  <p>And as for Sir <hi>JOHN PRESBYTER,</hi> this Court hath <hi>Voted</hi> him to the uncleane, filthy, impious, unholy, darke, and wordly <hi>Dungeon,</hi> called, <hi>JURE HUMANO,</hi> there with <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Biſhops,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>Grand-Presbyters,</hi> his <hi>Fore-fathers,</hi> to be faſt bound with the <hi>Majeſteriall Chaines</hi> of humaine <hi>Lawes, Ordinances, Edicts,</hi> &amp;c. and in them to be kept in ſafe cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy till the aforeſaid great <hi>Aſſiſes;</hi> in the <hi>Raigne</hi> of our <hi>Soveraigne Lord</hi> Chriſt, there, and then to be brought forth to the Tryall of that <hi>Great and terrible DAY. Now to the Priſoner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>PERSECUTION, hould up thy hand: Thou haſt been Indicted,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121057:27"/>
and Araigned of emnity againſt God and all goodnes, of Treaſons, Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, Bloodſhed, &amp;c. and for thy tryall haſt put thy ſelfe upon thy Countrey, which Countrey have found thee guilty, and to award the Sentence of death, from paſſing upon thee, thou haſt had the liberty this Court in juſtice could permit, to make thy defence: we have heard thine allegations, evaſions, the the Reaſons and Pleaes of thy Defendants, to whom was given all freedome of Defence could be deſired, alſo We have heard the diſtracted jubitaine me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diation of J. <hi>Conformity</hi> in thy behalfe, yet notwithſtanding all that can be made for thee, thy guilt is ſo palpably apparant and groſſe, that all the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilety, craft, and policy thou and thy Confederates can deviſe, cannot obſcure thee from the eye of juſtice: for this Court upon thy tryall, hath found out thy villany, Treaſon, and Bloodſhed, and how thou art guilty of all that is laid to thy charge: Therefore the Sentence of this Court is, that thou ſhalt returne to the place from whence thou cameſt, to wit, the noyſome, and filthy CAGE <hi>of every uncleane and hatefull Bird,</hi> the GLERGIE of Chriſtendome, there to be faſt bound with <hi>Inquiſition, Synaddicall, Claſſicall, Preiſt-bitter-all Chaines</hi> untill the Appearing of that Great and terrible Judge of the whole Earth, who ſhall take thee alive, with Sir SYMON, and his Son Sir JOHN, and eaſt thee with them and their Confederates into the LAKE of fire and brimſtone, where the Beaſt and the Falſe Prophet are, there to be cormented day and night for ever, and ever.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rev. 19. 1. 2. 3. And after theſe things I heard a great voyce of much people in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying, Allelujah: ſalvation and glory, honour and power, unto the Lord our God:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For true and righteous are his judgments, for he hath judged the Great Where, which did corrupt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Earth with her Fornication, and avenged the blood of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants at her band. Again they ſaid, Allelujah: And her ſmoak roſe up for ever &amp; ever.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>The POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>Leaſt the honeſt innocent intentions of Yong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e MARTIN ſhould receive ſome Synod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicall miſconſtruction, he deſires to be his owne Interpreter concerning ſome paſſages, and for the reſt he leaves so the fate of the publicke cenſure. Now whereas his Licence may ſeem to be an immitation of an Order of Parliament, it is only to ſhew the eſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, pride, and vaine glory of the boaſting Presbyters. And whereas he aſcribeth many Epithites, as, divine, holy &amp;c. to the Ordinance for Tythes, they are not intended in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſion to the Parliament, or to any of their Lawes, Statutes, or Ordinances whatſoever, but are uſed in the fence of Presbyterian acceptation, and of the reverend eſtimation they would perſwade us of that above any other whatſoever. And the uſe of the late League and Covenant, is likewiſe only in the Presbyterian ſence, ſimply reſpecting that Tribe, according to Edwards Inerpretation thereof. Honeſt MARTIN would not be miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, he is no enemie to the vnity of the two Kingdomes in Civill League and peace, but it is his hearts deſire and prayres, that not only they, but that all the Nations of the Earth were ſo in themſelues and one with another. And for the Advance of the Scots, that is uſed, only to ſhew, how thoſe Presbyterian Jeſuites would make that, which the two Kingdomes intend for the common good, to be perveted only to the Advance of their perſecuting Faction: And this MARTIN proclaimes to be his own genuine meaning.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:121057:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
